[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
科尔顿·奥格登：大家好
COLTON OGDEN: Hello, everybody.
欢迎来到GD50第二讲
Welcome to GD50 Lecture 2.
这里是越狱频道
This is Breakout.
有趣的是 CS50与Breakout有渊源
And interestingly, CS50 has a history with Breakout,
所以我今天调出了这个
so I pulled this up today.
这是2015、2014年的Pset3
This is Pset3 in 2015, 2014.
它是使用斯坦福便携的Breakout的实现
It was an implementation of Breakout using the Stanford Portable
库 这是一种Java库
Library, which was a sort of Java library
我们能够为其获得C绑定
that we were able to get C bindings for.
因此 学生们能够实际实施
And so students were able to actually implement
这是一款当时还是CS50设备的游戏 是一个Linux发行版
a game what was at the time the CS50 appliance, which is a Linux distro.
但我只想说 那是--
But suffice to say that was--
哦 这也是个有趣的故事
oh, a funny story also.
我碰巧也为这个实现编写了激光程序
I happened to also write the lasers for this implementation back in the day.
我认为这是最早的代码之一
And I think that was one of the first bits of code
我在使用CS50的时候弄脏了自己的手
I got my hands dirty with when working with CS50.
所以今天在突破的背景下 我们将
So today in the context of Breakout, we'll
谈论一些我们还没有谈论过的不同的事情
be talking about a few different things that we haven't talked about yet.
其中最有可能的是雪碧薄片
Sprite sheets being chief among them most likely.
至少最明显的是这样
At least the most visibly so.
因此 精灵纸只是一种拍摄图像的方式 一张大图像
So sprite sheets are simply a way of taking an image, a large image,
而不是拆分 而不是加载单独的图像
and rather than splitting it, rather than loading individual images
对于你在游戏中的所有不同的东西
for all of your different things in the game,
不管是你的外星人还是你的球拍什么的 你可以把所有东西
whether it's your aliens or your paddles or whatnot, you can put everything
放入一张表中 然后使用矩形对该表进行索引
into one sheet and then just sort of index into that sheet using rectangles,
四人组
quads.
我们很快就会谈到
We'll talk about soon.
这将允许您只绘制该图像的子集
Which will allow you to just draw a subset of that image,
并因此将您的所有图稿压缩到一个文件中
and therefore condense all of your artwork just into one piece, one file.
我们将更多地讨论程序生成
We'll be talking a little bit more about procedural generation
在越狱的背景下
in the context of Breakout.
在这种情况下 我们将在游戏世界中铺设所有的砖
And in this case, we'll be laying out all the bricks in the game world
从程序上讲
procedurally.
因此 在这种情况下 不是使用相同的颜色集
So having instead of the same set of colors, in this case,
标准的布局是一排一排地放一堆相同颜色的砖
the standard layout is to have a bunch of the same colored bricks row by row.
我们实际上将实现一种动态生成方法
We'll actually implement a dynamic generation approach
并有一堆不同的酷布局 我们将看到
and have a bunch of different cool layouts we'll see.
实际上很容易就能得到可信的结果
And it's actually quite simple to achieve pretty believable results.
我们会在这场比赛中更好地管理状态
We'll manage state a little bit better in this game.
在我们有一些全局变量之前
So before we sort of had a couple of global variables
我们并没有每个州或全球州的概念
and we didn't really have the concept of a per state or a global state
在我们所有的州之间
that we were cleanly sort of sharing between all of our states
我们的国家机器
for our state machine.
但为了避免有一种污染的全球名称空间
But to avoid having sort of like a polluted global name space
为了让事情变得更干净
and to just sort of keep things a little bit cleaner,
我们最终会把所有重要的变量都作为我们的代码 你知道
we'll end up taking all of the important variables for our code like, you know,
玩家和任何其他实体
the player and any other entities.
砖块球
The bricks, the ball.
而不是让他们在我们的主要[听不见]
And rather than keep them in our main [INAUDIBLE],,
我们最终会转移他们
we'll end up shifting them.
我们会把他们从不同的州转移到不同的州
We'll sort of transfer them to and from the different states
通过状态机的enter方法
via the state machine's enter method.
实际上我们会有水平
We'll actually have levels.
这是一个渐进系统
So a progression system.
从第一层开始 往上走
So start at level one, go up.
然后在每一个级别上 我们将实现一个规模
And then with each level, we'll implement a scale
在砖块的生成方面
in terms of the generation of the bricks.
因此 我们将得到更高层次的砖和更多的点作为一个结果
So we'll get higher tiered bricks and more points as a result.
我们会有一个健康系统
We'll have a health system.
《心》与《塞尔达传说》相似
So hearts, in a similar fashion to Legend of Zelda.
粒子系统 这是一个非常重要的美学组成部分
Particle systems, which are a very important aesthetic component
2D游戏和3D游戏
to 2D games and 3D games.
粒子系统基本上是一堆产生的图像
Particle systems basically being a bunch of spawned images
你可以把它们聚在一起 放进一个小产卵器里
that you sort of cluster, you put into a little spawner,
以某种方式发射它们 给它们上色 对它们进行数学运算
emit them in a certain way, and color them, perform math on them,
并得到一些可信的效果 比如火和烟
and get sort of believable effects like fire and smoke
以及所有其他的事情
and all these other things that would otherwise
使用简单的动画并不容易
be not easy to do using simple animation,
但对粒子系统来说微不足道
but trivial with a particle system.
我们会用球拍做一个更复杂的碰撞检测
We'll do a little bit more complicated collision detection with our paddle
比我们和乒乓的关系要好得多
and with our bricks than we did with Pong.
最后我们还会讨论
And then we'll also talk lastly about how
我们可以将数据本地保存到我们的计算机上 这样当我们关闭应用程序时
we can save data locally to our computer so that when we close the application
再运行一次 我们最终得到了一个持续的高分
and run it again, we end up having a persistent high score rather
而不仅仅是一些不稳定的东西
than just something that's volatile.
所以首先 我想演示一下今天完成的游戏
So first though, I would like to demo today's finished game.
因此 如果有人想从观众那里演示一下 那就太好了
So if anybody would like to demo from the audience, that would be nice.
来吧 上来吧
Go ahead and come up.
我先走一步 为你做好准备
I'll go ahead and cue it up for you.
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
杰里米：杰里米
JEREMY: Jeremy.
科尔顿·奥格登：杰里米
COLTON OGDEN: Jeremy.
科尔顿
Colton.
杰里米：很高兴认识你 科尔顿
JEREMY: Nice to meet you, Colton.
科尔顿·奥格登：很高兴见到你
COLTON OGDEN: Nice to meet you.
因此 我们将继续在这里运行Breakout
So we're going to go ahead and run Breakout here.
所以它使用了箭头键
And so it uses the arrow keys.
所以如果你继续往上按 然后往下按
So if you go ahead and press up and down,
你会看到你可以在开始屏幕和高分屏幕之间移动
you'll see you can move between the start and the high score screen.
所以它们是两个独立的屏幕
So they're two separate screens.
所以去吧 然后--
So go ahead and--
在我们这里 当你开始的时候 你可以选择一个球拍
here we have when you start, you can choose a paddle.
因此 你可以选择 而不是每次都是同样的老牌球拍
So rather than just the same old paddle every time, you get to select.
正如你在这里看到的 他选择了绿色
And as you can see here, he chose green.
所以他拿到了绿色球拍
So he gets the green paddle.
这些砖都是程序生成的
These bricks all procedure generated.
因此 如果他运行应用程序 它们将完全不同
So if he runs the application, they'll be completely different.
就像经典的公式一样 球移动
And as is the classic formula, the ball moves
在砖头和球拍之间
between the bricks and the paddle.
当它击中砖块时 如果它是某种颜色的
When it hits a brick, if it's of a certain color,
它要么被摧毁--在这种情况下 如果它是蓝色的
it'll either get destroyed-- in this case, if it's blue,
这是基色砖
it's the base color brick.
所以这是最低的值
So it's the lowest value.
如果它比蓝色高 它最终会变成
And if it's higher than blue, it'll end up
根据颜色的不同向下调整颜色
going down a color depending on which color it is.
我相信它会变成蓝色、绿色、红色、紫色、黄色
I believe it goes blue, green, red, purple, yellow.
因此 任何更高的东西都会被下移
So anything higher will get shifted down.
然后玩家积累分数 如你在右上角所看到的
And then the player amasses points, as you can see top right.
得分
Score.
还要注意这三颗心
And notice also the three hearts.
这将是球员的健康
That will be the player's health.
所以如果他可能故意输掉比赛
So if he were to lose on purpose possibly,
我们可以看到他收到了另一条消息 说按Enter键服务
we can see he gets another message that's saying press Enter to serve.
他的心跳下降了一分
His hearts have gone down by one.
所以现在他有三分之二的健康状况
So now he's got two out of three health.
所以最终 如果他碰巧完全输了--
And so eventually if he were to by chance lose completely--
噢
oh.
老实说 这是越狱最有趣的部分
That's honestly the most fun part about Breakout
只是让它卡在一堆东西里
is just getting it caught in a bunch of stuff.
但你可以看到我们在屏幕上观看了一场比赛
But you can see we go to a Game Over screen.
它会显示你的最终分数
It shows your final score.
然后你可以按Enter 它就会--
And then you can press Enter and it will--
噢
oh.
我一定是染上了虫子
I must have had a bug.
但这应该会把你带回--
But that should take you back to the--
如果你的分数很高
if in the event that you have a high score,
你要打出一个高分才行
it'll take you to enter a high score.
如果你的分数不高 它会把你带回开始菜单
And if you don't have a high score, it'll take you back to the Start menu.
所以我在最后一刻做了几处改动
So I made a couple of last minute changes.
不幸的是 我一定是把什么东西落在里面了
Unfortunately I must have left something in there.
但简而言之 这就是突破
But that's Breakout in a nutshell.
我们今天的目标是基本实现我们看到的所有功能
Our goal today will be to implement basically all the functionality we saw.
哦 我们没有看高分屏幕
Oh, we didn't take a look at the high score screen.
所以让我们也快速地来看看这一点
So let's take a look at that really quick as well.
所以在这里的冠军 你可以看到我们有起跑和高分
So here at the title, you can see we have Start and High Scores.
哦 伙计
Oh, man.
好的
OK.
我一定是搞砸了什么
I must have screwed something up.
所以我要去参加[INAUDIBLE]突破12
So I'm going want to go [INAUDIBLE] Breakout 12.
好的
OK.
抱歉的
Sorry.
我向你道歉
I apologize.
我会解决这个问题的
I'm going to fix that.
但它应该在这里显示这个菜单 在这里您将有一个包含您所有姓名的列表
But it should show this menu here where you will have a list of all your names
从文件中加载 并相应地输出您的分数
that get loaded from a file and will output your score accordingly.
如果你得到了新的最高分
And in the event that you get a new high score,
在那之后你可以输入你的名字
you'll get to enter your name after that,
然后 它将最终将其保存到另一个文件
and then it will end up saving it to another file.
当我们达到这一点时 我会试着修复它
And when we get to that point I'll try and fix it
这样我们才能真正看到它的样子
so that we can actually see what it looks like.
所以让我们回到这些幻灯片上来
So let's go back to these slides here.
这就是我们游戏的整体状态和流程
So this is the overall state, flow of our game.
所以你可以看到 我用高亮的颜色把它标出来
So as you can see by me marking it out in a highlighted color,
我们从StartState开始
we start off in the StartState.
这些都是我们以前讲过的内容
And this is all stuff we've covered before.
只有状态机
Just the state machine.
它比Flappy Bird要复杂一点
It's a little bit more complicated than Flappy Bird.
我们有八个州 而不是我认为的
We have eight states as opposed to I think it
上一节课有四五个人
was four or five in the last lecture.
箭头显示了哪些状态可以在其他状态之间移动
And the arrows illustrate which states can move in between other states.
如我们所见 StartState可以通过向上和向下箭头移动
So as we saw, the StartState can move via the up and down arrows
在High ScoreState
in the HighScoreState.
它可以在HighScoreState和Back之间移动
It can move between the HighScoreState and back.
所以当你进入HighScoreState时 按Escape键
So when you go into the HighScoreState, press Escape,
回到StartState
go back to the StartState.
StartState也有一个分支箭头
The StartState also has an arrow branching off
向左一直到PaddleSelectState
to the left going down to the PaddleSelectState
我们看到用户能够选择要使用的划桨
where we saw the user is able to select a paddle to use.
一旦他们选择了划桨 我们就去ServeState
Once they've selected a paddle, we'll go to the ServeState.
他们将能够悠闲地发球
They'll be able to serve the ball at their leisure.
然后它将在PlayState之间来回移动
And then it will go back and forth between the PlayState.
因此 如果他们最终受到损害 球
So if they end up taking damage, the ball
在屏幕表面以下 它们将返回到ServeState
goes below the surface of the screen, they'll go back to the ServeState
这样他们才能重新定位自己
again so they can reorient themselves.
如果他们在PlayState 他们最终得分
If they're in the PlayState and they end up scoring,
清理整套砖 他们会
clearing the whole entire set of bricks, they'll
实际上被带到了维克托州
actually get taken to the VictoryState.
而VictoryState是我们增加级别的地方
And the VictoryState is where we increment the level
我们还重新生成了级别
and we also regenerate the level.
而VictoryState回到ServeState
And the VictoryState goes back to the ServeState,
然后我们再重复一遍整个循环
and then we repeat that whole loop again.
在PlayState 如果他们想要结束一场比赛
In the PlayState if they are to get a Game Over,
他们会去GameOverState 它会告诉他们他们的分数
they'll go to the GameOverState, it'll tell them their score,
然后他们会进入EnterHighScoreState
and then they'll go to the EnterHighScoreState
取决于他们的分数是否很高
depending on whether they have a high score.
如果不是 如向上和向左的箭头所示
And if not, as seen by the arrow that goes up and to the left,
他们实际上会回到星际之州
they'll actually go back to the StartState.
然后EnterHighScoreState也将返回到HighScoreState
And then the EnterHighScoreState will also go back to the HighScoreState
这样他们一进门就能看到
so that they can see once they've entered
他们的高分 他们的分数相对于列表中的其他分数
their high score, their score relative to the other scores in the list.
所以在我们现在要看的《突破0》中
So in Breakout0, which we're going to look at now,
我们要做一些非常基本的事情
we're going to do some very basic stuff.
因此 这是一如既往的第0天更新
So this is the Day 0 update as always.
我现在在《越狱0》里
I'm in Breakout0 right now.
是的 我是
Yes, I am.
所以我们要做的是 我们首先来看这里的第27行
So what we're going to do is we're going to look at first thing here, line 27.
所以在我们在应用程序中所做的事情之前
So before what we were doing in our application
基本上在顶层有很多文件 有点迷失了方向
is having basically a lot of files at the top level and sort of losing track
我们可能在做什么
of what we were doing potentially.
特别是当你开始添加越来越多的文件
Especially as you start adding more and more files
还有50到100个文件
and you've got like 50, 100 more files, that's
一些明显不重要的东西
something that's obviously not maintainable.
所以解决的办法是 把它们放在文件夹里
So the solution there, just put them in folders
然后记录所有的事情
and then keep track of everything.
让他们有组织
Keep them organized.
这是我们要开始做的一件大事
And that's a major thing that we're going to start doing.
最重要的是 在代码中
And on top of that, we're also going to, in our code,
让事情变得更加模块化
keep things a little bit more modular.
这就是为什么我们有这个文件源斜杠依赖项
And that's why we have this file source slash dependencies,
我们马上就会看到
which we'll take a look at in a second.
我们在这里分配了一堆全局表
We've allocated a bunch of global tables here.
所以我们的设计决定
So we're taking the design decision of even
虽然我提到过我们会把很多全局变量
though I mentioned that we will be sort of taking a lot of the global variables
从我们的应用程序资产中
out of our application assets, we're going to keep
所有这些都是全局变量
all of those in some global variables.
将来我们会看到如何实现资源管理器
And we'll see in the future how we can maybe implement a resource manager
为我们解决这个问题
class that takes care of this for us.
但现在 为了简单起见 在爱 负荷
But for now, for simplicity's sake, in love.load,
我们只需要几个全局表
we're just going to have a few global tables that contain,
在本例中是全局字体
in this case, global fonts.
通过键 我们可以索引小 中 大字体
So by key, we can index small, medium, and large fonts,
就是不同大小的新字体
which are just new fonts at different sizes.
八十六三十二
8, 16, 32.
我们正在利用它
And we're using it.
我们现在有一个字体文件夹 而不仅仅是保持在父级
We have a fonts folder now instead of just keeping it at the parent level.
我们将把它设置为小
We're going to set it to small.
我们有全局纹理
We have global textures.
背景 主 箭头 红心 粒子
So background, main, arrows, hearts, particle.
所以我们有背景 这是我们屏幕的背景
So we have the background, which was the background of our screen.
我们所有的砖块球拍球等等都在总部
Main has all of our bricks, paddles, the balls, et cetera.
箭头将用于桨选择屏幕
Arrows are going to be for the paddle select screen.
两个左右箭头
The two left and right arrows.
心脏是为了我们的健康
Hearts are going to be for our health.
粒子是一个很小很小的纹理
And then particle is a single, small, tiny little texture
我们将用它来产生粒子系统中的所有粒子
that we'll use to spawn all the particles in our particle systems
稍后当我们接近演示的尾声时
later on as we get towards the end of the demonstration.
所以这是推
So this is push.
我们就像平常一样布置
We're setting it up just like normal.
没什么新鲜的
Nothing new there.
除了虚拟宽度 虚拟高度 以及所有这些东西
Except the virtual width, virtual height, and all that stuff,
如果我们在一个常量文件中查看源代码 这些都被移走了
those have been moved out, if we look into source in a constants file.
所以这个文件 没有包含main中的所有常量
So this file here, instead of having all the constants in main,
把它们拿出来
it kind of makes sense just to take them out, put them
在一个名为constants.lua的文件中 我们可以排序管理所有这些
in a file called constants.lua, and we can sort manage all that.
当我们看到资本窗口时
We can know immediately when we're looking at capital window
宽度 窗户高度 等等
width, window height, et cetera.
这些都是常量
And these are all constants.
如果你有一个常量文件 我们可以更容易地
If you have a constants file, we just can more easily
追踪它而不是抓取我们所有的文件
track it rather than having to grab through all of our files
试图弄清楚我们在看什么
to try and figure out what we were looking at.
和前面一样 常量在设置屏幕中使用
And the constants are used here in our set up screen as before.
然后另一个声音全局表 就像以前一样
And then another sounds global table, just as before.
我们有很多不同的音效
We have a bunch of different sound effects.
我把音乐和音效分开了
I've separated the music from the sound effects
就为了让我们一眼就能看出来 哦 这是音乐
just so that we can see at a glance, oh, this is the music,
这些是音效
these are the sound effects.
很直接
Pretty straight forward.
我们有一个国家机器 一如既往
We have a state machine, as always.
我们将使用StartState来进行演示
And we're just going to use a StartState for this demonstration.
将其设置为开始
Setting it to Start.
爱 调整大小 爱 更新
Love.resize, love.update.
这些都是我们以前见过的函数
These are all functions we've seen before.
没什么新鲜的
Nothing too new.
Love.keypress.
我们有一个全局输入表
We have a global input table.
就像Flappy Bird一样 我们可以在任何地方索引输入表
So as in the case of Flappy Bird, we can index into that input table anywhere
在我们的应用程序中调用love.keyboard.wasPressed[key]
in our application and call love.keyboard.wasPressed[key],
它允许我们专门从main获取输入并使用它
which allows us to take input exclusively from main and use it
在其他模块中
in other modules.
这里我们画的是
Here we're drawing the--
这是实际的渲染代码
so this is the actual rendering code.
我们在我们的爱中这样做 draw与特定的状态相对
And we're doing this in our love.draw as opposed to a specific state
因为这实际上适用于所有州
because this is actually going to apply to all states.
我们总是会有这样的背景
We're always going to have this background.
所以与其一遍又一遍地重复
So rather than duplicate it over and over again,
在本例中 这一小段代码
in this instance, this minor bit of code,
我们将显示所有状态后面的背景
we're going to display the background behind all the states.
所以所有的州都将在这个背景下渲染
So all the states are going to render over this background
让它看起来更有凝聚力
and make it seem a little more cohesive.
我们将在没有旋转的情况下画0 0
We're going to draw at 0, 0 without rotation.
然后这里有一些数学运算 即虚拟宽度
And then this bit of math here, the virtual width
除以 然后背景宽度减去1 最终得到一个比例因子
divided by, and then background width minus one, end up being a scale factor
这样我们就可以始终将其调整到我们的虚拟宽度
so that we can always scale it to be our virtual width.
因为默认情况下纹理比实际窗口小一些
Because the texture by default is some amount smaller than our actual window
或者我们的实际虚拟宽度和高度 但通过除以虚拟宽度
or our actual virtual width and height, but by dividing virtual width
无论该图像的背景宽度是多少
by whatever the background width of that image is by one,
我们将获得比例因子 因为虚拟宽度大于图像
we'll get a scale factor because virtual width is larger than the image.
我们将得到X和Y的比例因子 它等同于它完全拉伸
We'll get a scale factor on X and Y that equates to it completely stretching
来填满我们的虚拟宽度和高度
to fill our virtual width and height.
回想一下 这两个参数是X和Y上的比例
And recall that these two parameters are the scale on the X and the Y.
所以这将是一些 就像 一点什么或两点什么
So it's going to be some, like, one point something or two point something.
不惜一切代价来填满屏幕
Whatever it takes to end up filling the screen.
最后 在这里 我实现的新Bit
And then lastly here, the new bit I implemented
只是一个每秒显示帧的函数 我认为
is just a display of frames per second function, which I think
通常是很重要的 而且很容易做到
is kind of important generally, and it's very easy to do.
我不记得了 我想我们还没谈过 但只是
I don't recall, I don't think we talked about it yet, but just
Love.timer.getFPS
love.timer.getFPS.
然后我就在左上角画上绿色
And then I just draw in the top left in green
这样我们就可以在游戏的所有迭代中看到它 什么
so that we can see it throughout all of our iterations of the game, what
每秒的帧数是
are frames per second are.
如果您想要在无需查看终端或任何东西的情况下进行监控
If you want to monitor without having to look through your terminal or anything
就像这样 就在上面显示 它是
like that, just displaying at the top, it's
这是很多比赛中的标准练习
standard practice in a lot of games.
如果您已进入调试控制台或诸如此类的
If you've gone to the debug console or whatnot
或者是调查了一些黑客行为
or sort of looked into some of the hacks,
你会在很多地方看到这一点
you'll see that in a lot of places.
所以我早些时候谈到了依赖
So I talked earlier about dependencies.lua.
因此 这也与我们将一切模块化的努力联系在一起
So this ties in as well to our effort to sort of modularize everything,
保持一切井然有序
keep everything organized.
而不是要求所有东西都放在Main的顶部
Instead of requiring everything at the top of main,
让我们把它们都放在一个文件里 然后我们
let's just put it all in a file and then we'll
一目了然地知道我们需要什么 我们不必查看Main
know at a glance what we're requiring and we don't have to look through main
并建造100条主线 这可能比需要的要多得多
and make main 100 lines, potentially a lot more than it needs to be.
所以需要推动 需要上进
So requiring push, requiring class.
和我们以前做的一样
Same as we've done before.
需要Soure.Constants
Require source.constants.
我们有权访问这些文件
We have access to those.
需要StateMachine 然后是BaseState和StartState
Require StateMachine, and then BaseState and StartState.
那么 让我们继续来看看我们的StartState
So let's go ahead and take a look at our StartState.
所以我把州放在了SOURCE的子文件夹中
So I put states in a subfolder of source.
这是另一种让事情保持模块化的努力
This is another effort to sort of keep things modular.
在这个特定的项目中 我们不会有很多嵌套的代码文件夹
In this particular project, we won't have a lot of nested folders of code,
但我决定把各州放在他们自己的文件夹里
but I decided to put the states in their own folder
你可以很容易地访问你所有的州
just so easily you can get access to all your states.
因此 我们将在这里的第21行查看StartState
So we'll look at StartState here on line 21.
回想一下 在StartState中 我们刚刚在屏幕中央显示了Breakout
So recall in the StartState, we just had Breakout in the center of the screen
然后我们有了首发比赛和高分
and then we had Start Game and High Scores.
因此 用户能够突出显示他想要查看的州
So the user was able to highlight which state he wanted to look at.
因此 我们需要跟踪突出显示的是哪一个
So we need to keep track of which one is highlighted.
所以所有这个变量的目的只是为了跟踪
So all this variable's purpose is just to keep track.
那就一两个吧
So one or two.
一个是玩游戏 两个是高分
One being Play Game, and two being High Scores.
然后在这里 如果我们上下按压 那么我们--
And then here if we press up and down, then we--
因为实际上只有两种选择
because there's only two options effectively,
你可以只用一两个来翻转任何高亮的部分
you can just flip whatever highlight is with one or two.
如果你有一个多于两个的选项列表
If you have a list of options that's more than two,
你需要递增一个 直到它到达任何
you'll need to increment one until it gets to whatever
X是您的列表选项的数量
X is, your number of list options.
然后如果你在那个点按下
And then if you press down at that point,
你应该翻到最上面去
you should flip back up to the top.
同样的道理也适用于你是否选择了第一种选择
And the same holds true for whether you're at option one.
你应该去翻转 旋转到你的清单的底部
You should go flip, rotate to the bottom of your list
这样看起来你就像是绕了一圈
so that it looks as if you've gone all the way around.
然后--当我们这样做的时候 我们只是在这里播放声音
And-- then we're just playing a sound here when we do that.
我们有一个love.keyboard.wa按下[退出]调用
We have a love.keyboard.wasPressed[escape] call
这里
here.
它不再是全局的 因为我们的应用程序中有一些状态
It's not global anymore because there are some states in our application
我们可能想按下Escape来后退
where we might want to press Escape to actually go backwards,
我们会看到的
and we'll see that.
在这里渲染
And so rendering here.
我们用大字体渲染Breakout
We render Breakout with a large font.
现在我们可以在屏幕中央的大键处访问G字体
Now that we can access G fonts at large key in the center of the screen,
设置中等字体
set medium font.
然后我们将一个接一个地呈现两个文本字段
And then we're going to render our two text fields one after the other.
但如果高亮部分等于1
But if highlighted is equal to one, then we're
将它设置为蓝色 这是三种颜色之一
going to set it to some blue color, which is one of three--
255 255 255
255, 255, 255.
然后将其渲染
And then render it.
然后确保在那之后重置颜色 因为回想一下
And then make sure to reset the color after that because recall
爱情2D本身就像一个状态机
love 2D is sort of like a state machine in its own right,
如果你给某个东西设置颜色 不管你画什么
where if you set the color to something, whatever you draw and render
然后呢 不管是图片还是文字 都会采用这个颜色
after that, be it images or text, will adopt that color.
所有的都是255 255 255 255
So having everything be 255, 255, 255, 255,
它是纯白色的 完全不透明
which is pure white, completely opaque, has
把所有东西都画成完全不透明的效果
the effect of drawing everything completely opaque.
但如果你不这样做 你的图像或你后来画的东西
But if you don't do that, your images or whatnot that you draw afterwards
会是有色的或透明的 这是你大多数时候不想要的
will be tinted or transparent, which you most of the time don't want.
但有时候你可能会想要
But you might sometimes want that, and we'll actually
在PaddleSelectState中可以看到
see that in the PaddleSelectState.
同样的道理也适用于这里
And same thing holds true here.
如果突出显示的是两个 则执行完全相同的操作
If highlighted is two, do the exact same thing.
如果我们运行这个应用程序
And so if we run this application, which is mainly
只是我们之前看到的一个子集 我们可以上下移动
just a subset of what we saw before, we can move up and down
在开始和最高分之间
between Start and High Scores.
但如果我们按下任何一个回车键
But if we press Enter on any of them, nothing
因为我们没有事件处理程序来处理它
happens because we have no event handlers actually taking care of that.
但是我们有缩放到屏幕上的图像 我们有中间的突破
But we have the image scaled to the screen, we have Breakout in the middle,
我们有两个菜单选项
and we have our two menu options there.
所以Breakout 1.
So Breakout1.
这就是我们开始深入精灵表的地方
So this is where we start to dive a little bit into sprite sheets, which
是游戏开发的主要组成部分 2D游戏
is a major component of game development, 2D game
我们将在未来和这个应用程序中看到的发展
development that we'll be looking at in the future and in this application.
但最终 精灵表单只是 而不是有--
But a sprite sheet is just, ultimately, rather than have--
我不知道这张精灵纸上有多少张图片
I don't know how many images there are on this sprite sheet here.
但无论这些文件有多少 只要有
But however many of these files, just have
一个文件将它们放在一起 然后使用矩形定义
one file put them all together, and then using rectangles, define
所有不同的精灵都在那里
where all the different sprites are.
然后当我们想要画的时候 使用这些矩形
And then when we want to draw, use those rectangles
告诉我爱 图解 画 我要你
and just tell love.graphics.draw, I want you
来绘制这个纹理 这个精灵图案 但是我想
to draw this texture, this sprite sheet, but I want
你只需要画它的这一部分.
you to draw just this section of it.
你会在一个四边形中传递它 这个四边形只是一个简单的矩形 上面有高度 X和Y
You'd pass it in a quad, which is just simply rectangle with height, X and Y.
喜欢2D的人会知道 好的 我要画这个图像 但只有这一点
And love 2D will know, OK, I'm going to draw the image, but only this bit.
它的效果就像你只画了很小的图像
And it has the effect of looking as if you're only drawing tiny little images
而不是一个可怕的形象
as opposed to one monstrous image.
以及与我们要查看的相关函数
And the functions that are relevant for us to look at
是love.graph ics.newquad 它接受X、Y、宽度和高度
are love.graphics.newquad, which takes an X, Y, width, and a height.
还有一个维度对象 这是从图像中获得的
And also a dimensions object, which you get from an image.
我们会看到的
We'll see that.
我相信 所有这些基本上只是一个X Y 宽度和高度
And all that basically is, I believe, is just an X, Y, width and height as well.
或者只是宽度和高度 更确切地说 来自任何图像
Or just a width and a height, rather, from whatever image
您想要为创建四边形
you want to create quads for.
然后是爱 画 画 我们已经看过了
And then love.graphics.draw, we've already seen it,
但这是一个不同的签名
but this is a different signature.
这有纹理 四边形 X Y 四边形是第二个参数
This has texture, quad, X, Y. Quad being the second argument.
当它进入这个四边形时 它知道只有抽签
And when it takes in this quad, it knows to only draw
定义的矩形图像显示在屏幕上
that defined rectangle of image to the screen.
接下来 我们将继续关注《突破1》
And so we'll go ahead and take a look now at Breakout1.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 有没有什么工具
COLTON OGDEN: The question was, are there any tools
这样我们在做床单的时候就不用去猜四合院在哪里了？
so that we don't have to guess where the quad is when we're doing the sheet?
是的 有很多时间
Yes, there are a lot of the time.
我看了看 看到了几个 但我自己还没有彻底测试过它们
I looked and saw a couple, but I haven't tested them thoroughly myself.
对于像这样的简单示例 通常是
For simpler examples like this, it's usually
非常简单 可以通过编程来完成
easy enough to programmatically do it.
但是的 当你开始阅读巨型精灵地图集时
But yeah, when you get into having giant sprite atlases where
你有特别的东西不一定是对称的
you have especially things that are not necessarily symmetrical
或者看起来是矩形的 尽管它们仍然需要被限定为矩形
or rectangular looking even though they still need to be defined rectangularly,
通常最好使用这样的工具
it's often best to use a tool like that.
有 我相信 我只是没有使用它们
There are, I do believe, I just haven't used them.
我可以在以后的讲座中提出来 这样我们就可以讨论了
I can bring it up in a future lecture so we can discuss.
在我们进入Breakout 1之前还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions before we carry into Breakout1?
好吧
All right.
所以我将打开第一个
So I'm going to go ahead and open up the very first thing
我们应该在Breakout 1上看看
we should look at on Breakout1.
在源目录中 我们有一个新文件
In the source directory, we have a new file.
从现在开始 我假设
And from here on out, I'm going to assume,
我们总是假设当我们引入一个新文件时
we're going to always assume that when we introduce a new file,
我们将把它包含在dependencies. lua中
we're going to include it in dependencies.lua.
所以在这种情况下 我们只需要说require source/util
And so in this case, all we need to do is just say require source/util.
正如你所看到的 我们还在这个演示中添加了一个PlayState
And as you can see, we're also adding a PlayState to this demonstration.
但从现在开始 我不会再提我们了
But from here on out, I won't make mention of us actually
将其添加到我们的项目中
adding it to our project.
所以util.lua是包含代码的模块
So util.lua is the module that contains the code
我们将使用它来为给定的精灵表生成四边形
we're going to use to actually generate quads for a given sprite sheet.
这个函数 它所做的就是 它需要一个地图集或精灵表--
And this function, all it does, is it takes an atlas or sprite sheet--
这两个名字是同义的
the names are synonymous.
你会听到他们两个
You'll hear them both.
或者我们给它一个地图集 我们给它我们想要的瓷砖的宽度
Or we pass it an Atlas, we pass it the width of the tile that we want
和瓷砖的高度
and the height of the tile that we want.
它会得到纸张的宽度和高度
It's going to get the width and the height of the sheet here.
所以每幅图像都有一个函数叫做获取宽度和高度
So every image has a function called get width and get height,
所以我们就这么做
so we're just going to do that.
特别是纸张的宽度和高度
And specifically the sheet width and sheet height
是图像的宽度除以图块宽度和图块高度
are the width of the image divided by tile width and tile height.
这样我们就知道我们需要在精灵表上重复多少次
So we know how many times we need to iterate over the sprite sheet
来生成矩形
to generate a rectangle.
我们根据瓷砖的大小来划分
We're dividing it up based on the size of our tiles.
然后我们在这里做一个简单的嵌套四个循环
And then we just basically do a simple nested four loop here.
我们开始一个计数器和一个精灵表
We start a counter and a sprite sheet.
这个精灵表将是一个表 容纳我们所有的四边形
This sprite sheet is going to be a table that holds all of our quads.
我们只说Y 得到零
We just say for Y, get zero.
图纸高度减一
Sheet height minus one.
所以从左上角开始往下走
So starting at the top left, going down.
从顶部开始向下 然后x等于零
And starting at the top going down, and then x equals zero,
从左边开始向右转
starting at the left going right.
在Sprite Sheet Sheet Counter 这是一个因为在Lua
At sprite sheet, sheet counter, which is one here because in lua,
表是一个索引表
tables are one indexed.
我们将创建一个新的四边形 X乘以瓷砖宽度 Y乘以瓷砖宽度
We're going to create a new quad at X times tile width, Y times tile width.
给它和我们的瓷砖一样的宽度和高度
Give it the width and the height of our tile.
所以 无论我们传递给函数签名的是什么
So just whatever we passed into our function signature.
在这种情况下 通常是16x32
Here it will often be in this case be 16 by 32
因为这就是砖块的大小
because that's the size of the bricks.
然后我们传入幻灯片中看到的最后一个参数
And then we pass in the last parameter that we saw in the slide,
这就是地图集：获取维度
which is atlas:getdimensions.
然后我们只需在这里增加我们的床单计数器
And then we just increment our sheet counter here.
然后在这个结束的时候 当我们都做完了 我们会把这个还回去
And then at the end of this, when we're all done, we'll return this.
我们会有一张四合院的桌子 然后我们就可以
We'll have a table of quads that we can then
以一、二、三、四、五、六、七、八的形式使用
use that are in a sort of one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
嗯 我应该说 一 二 三 四 五 六 七 八
Well, I should say, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight top
从左到右是我们床单上所有的精灵
left to bottom right of all the sprites in our sheet to make it
看起来超级简单
super easy to look at.
我们这里还有一个功能
We have another function here.
默认情况下 Lua没有切片功能 但我们只是在添加它
Lua doesn't by default, have a slice function, but we are just adding to it.
桌子 切片
Table.slice.
它首先获取表 表中我们想要的第一个条目
It takes the table a first, the first entry in the table that we want,
最后一个条目 然后是它们之间的步骤
the last entry, and then the step between them.
就像Pythons切片函数一样 它只是迭代
Just like Pythons slice function, it just iterates over the
For循环 这是倒数第一个循环
for loop, which is first till one.
因此 默认情况下只有一个 直到最后或者直到任何这样的数字符号
So one by default. Until the last or until whatever this sort of number sign
是一张桌子的大小 我想我们还没有介绍过
is the size of a table, which I don't think we've introduced yet.
但基本上 如果我们最后通过 它就会止步于此 否则
But basically, if we pass in last, it'll stop there, otherwise just
假设我们想要整个表
assume we want the whole entire table.
然后这个逗号在末尾 它有一步或一步
And then this comma here at the end, which has step or one,
您可以在for循环的末尾传入一个步骤作为第三个参数
you can pass in a step at the end of a for loop as a third argument,
这将会增加或减少你所处的循环
and that will be however much increments or decrements the loop that you're in.
因此 默认情况下 只有一个
So by default, just one.
我们先走一步 然后走到第二步 再走到第三步
We go one, then we go to two, then we go to three.
但您可以将其设置为负1
But you can set it to negative one.
所以如果你说四 我得到三减一
And so if you say four i gets three to one minus one,
你来三 二 一
you'll go three, two, one.
而且你不能正常地走一步 而我们这里就是这样做的
And you can't do normally a step, which is what we do here.
不 你可以走一步 但你不能切开
No, you can do a step, but you can't slice,
这就是为什么我们在这里以切片的数量加一得到表i
which is why we have here sliced at number of slice plus one gets table i,
然后最终我们返回Slice
and then eventually we return slice.
所以它只返回我们所在表的一部分
So it just returns just a segment of whatever table we're in.
然后这里的重要功能是 我们实际上
And then the important function here that we're actually
要在我们的应用程序中使用 我们将生成四足桨
going to use in our application, we're going to generate quads paddles.
所以这需要X和Y 0和64
And so this takes X and Y, 0 and 64.
如果我们回过头来看我们的桨 我们
And if we look back at our paddles here, we
可以看到我们有各种不同的尺码
can see that we have various different sizes.
所以我们有一个小的 一个中号的 一个大的 然后是一个非常大的
So we have a small one, a medium one, a large one, and then a really large one.
所以如果我们想把每一只桨都放在雪碧表上
So if we want to get every single paddle in our sprite sheet,
小、中、大、大 请注意 我们有四个街区
small, medium, large, giant, notice that we have four blocks
在每一块中 我们有四种不同的大小
and within each of those blocks we have four different sizes.
所以我们可以重复这四次
So we can just iterate over this four times
然后定义这个矩形的大小
and then just define whatever the size of this rect
就是那个教区 那个教区 那个教区
is, that rect, that rect, and that rect.
我们将在这里看到它的数学计算
And we'll see the math for it here.
如果我从零到三 对我来说 从零到三
If I go zero to three, for i, get zero till three.
我们要继续 因为这会给我们四个
We're going to go ahead because that will give us four.
这就是我们要在精灵工作表上迭代的次数
So that's how many times we want to iterate over the sprite sheet
才能得到单独的四元组
to get the separate quads.
我们会买最小的
We'll get the smallest one.
因此 四元组起了反作用
So quads counter.
我们将计数器初始化为1
We initialize counter to one.
得到了爱 图形 这个新的四边形在X Y 32和16
Gets love.graphics, that new quad at X, Y, with the 32 and 16.
哦 X和Y在这里默认为0和64 因为音符--
Oh, and X and Y default at 0 and 64 here because the note--
回想一下 这里的这些都是16个高的
recall that these are all 16 tall here.
所以我们从64开始 所以我们从这里开始
So we're starting Y at 64 so that we start right here.
我们从零开始 因为它在左边
And we're starting X at zero because it's on the left side.
所以我们就这么做
So we'll do that.
我们会递增计数器
We'll increment counter.
把它调到32宽16高
Get it at 32 wide by 16 tall.
这些是最小的一个的实际尺寸
Those are the actual dimensions of the smallest one.
同样的逻辑也适用于中型和大型企业
The same exact logic applies for medium and for large.
只是我们加了32 然后我们把它改成64号
Only that we're adding 32 and then we're making it size 64,
然后我们在96号的X上加96 因为它们变宽了
and then we're adding 96 to X at size 96 because they're getting wider,
但他们也在更多地向右倾斜
but they're also offsetting more to the right.
最后一点和以前几乎一样 除了现在我们
And then the last bit is pretty much the same thing as before, except now we're
将Y加16返回到X 因为我们在精灵工作表中排到了下一行
going Y plus 16 back to X because we've gone down a row in our sprite sheet
此时的桨宽为128 但仍为16像素
The paddle width at that point is 128, but still 16 pixels.
然后在底部 因为我们想要做四次
And then here at the bottom because we want to do this four times,
我们想要检查的块实际上是32个像素
we want to go through the chunks are effectively 32 pixels
因为我们要开到16 16 16 16
because we're going 16, 16, 16, 16.
我们要把32加到Y上 然后转到下一组四个球拍
We're going to add 32 to Y and then go to the next set of four paddles.
这就是我们如何有效地获得所有的划桨精灵
So this is how we're effectively getting all of the paddle sprites,
它们将从一个存储到X 我相信X是16
and they;re going to be stored one through X where I believe X is 16.
因此 我们将在精灵工作表中定义16个四边形
So we'll have 16 quads defined in our sprite sheet
之后 我们就可以回来了
thereafter that we can then return.
所以我要回到主要的 Lua 现在在64行
So I'm going to go back to main.lua now on line 64.
这里我们有一个新的全局表 名为GFRAMES
Here we have a new global table called gframes.
我们将能够在任何想要画东西的地方访问它
We'll be able to access this anywhere we want to draw stuff.
这和我们刚刚看到的是一样的
And it's just the same thing that we just saw.
生成四足桨 我们只是在我们的主纹理中传递它
Generate quads paddles, and we just pass it in our main texture.
我们的主要质地是这个
And our main texture is this.
这是我们的主要纹理看起来是什么样子
This is what our main texture looks like.
然后我们要将其编入索引
And then we're going to index it.
我们会说它得到了关键的控制板
We're going to say it gets the key paddles,
因为在那个特定的桌子上只有我们的球拍的四个方格
because in that particular table was just the quads for our paddles.
因此 在将来 我们只需要调用love.graph ics.Drawing纹理 然后
So in the future, we just need to call love.graphics.drawtexture and then
索引到框架划桨在任何我们想要的划桨
index into gframes paddles at whatever paddle we want.
这就是我们可以跟踪我们想要画的划桨明智的方式
And that's how we can keep track of what we want to draw paddle wise.
在这个特定的演示中 我们有一个新的Padle类
And in this particular demo we have a new paddle class
因为划桨是我们比赛中的一件事
because paddle is a thing in our game.
我们可以将其表示为某种类或对象
We can represent it as sort of a class or an object.
所以我们将为它定义一个类
So we'll define a class for it.
到目前为止 一切都很简单
Everything is pretty simple thus far.
得到X和Y Dx随高度为零
Gets an X and a Y. Dx is zero with height.
皮肤
Skin.
皮肤将是什么颜色的
The skin is going to be what color it is.
我们需要跟踪这一点
We need to keep track of that.
然后是大小 因为大小将是我们排序的偏移量
And then the size, because size will be how we sort of offset
进入我们的桨 我们的四肢 因为大小有小的 中等的 大的 巨大的
into our paddles, our quads, because the sizes are small, medium, large, giant.
一 二 三 四乘四
One, two, three, four times four.
所以第一盘一 二 三 四 然后五
So one, two, three, four for the first set and then five,
第二盘是六、七、八
six, seven, eight for the second set.
这些都是按颜色排列的
Those are all sort of by color.
所以我们可以乘以皮肤时间--
So we can just multiply skin times--
或者我们可以通过皮肤来繁殖我们的体型
or we can multiply whatever our size is by skin
这将为我们提供当前帧 即我们想要的当前四边形
and that will give us the current frame, the current quad that we want in order
画到屏幕上
to draw to the screen.
然后在7号线上--
And then on line seven--
这就是键盘输入
so this is keyboard input here.
我们以前见过的东西
Stuff that we've seen before.
如果我们按向左或向右 那么球拍应该会移动
If we're pressing left or right, then the paddles should move.
DX应设置为左侧或右侧
Dx should be set left or right.
我们想把它夹住
We want to clamp it.
我们看到了这个 我们也看到了这个
We saw this, we've seen this as well.
将输入夹在屏幕的左侧和右侧
Clamp the input to the left and the right side of the screen.
如果dx小于零 则执行math.max和math.min 否则
If the dx is less than zero, do math.max and math.min otherwise
如果我们要向右移动
if we're moving to the right.
然后在这里 这实际上是我们将所有东西联系在一起的地方
And then here, this is actually where we tie it all together
我们实际上使用四元组来在屏幕上绘制一些东西
and we actually use the quads to draw something onto the screen.
因此 我们将其命名为love.graph 只绘制我们的纹理 我们的主要纹理
So we're calling love.graphics.draw just our texture, our main texture.
然后在我们现在的大小 也就是两个人的球拍上画出格框
And then gframes at paddles at our current size, which is two.
默认情况下 我们想要中号外加四倍的
We want to by default have the medium size plus four times whatever
我们的皮肤是负一
our skin is, minus one.
因此 如果我们的皮肤是蓝色皮肤 我们不会向它添加任何东西
So if our skin is one, which is the blue skin, we won't add anything to it.
只会是零的四倍
It'll just be four times zero.
但如果我们有下一个 就会是二减一
But if we have the next one, it'll be two minus one,
所以我们最终会在上面加4
so we'll end up adding four to that.
因为无论皮肤是什么 我们都要加四倍
And because we're adding four to it times whatever that skin is,
它基本上会把我们四个四边形放进去
it will just basically put us four quads in,
哪一个是下一个 完全一样的球拍 但下一个颜色
which is the next, the exact same paddle, but the next color.
最后 我们要看的是PlayState
And then lastly what we'll look at here is the PlayState.
所以我们之前只有StartState 但是现在我们
So we had just the StartState before, but now we
我想测试一下 确保我们能画出一个桨
want to actually test to make sure we can draw a paddle,
在屏幕上移动
move it around the screen.
所以我们要在这里实现一个简单的PlayState
So we're going to implement a simple PlayState here.
所以在第20行 我们只是打电话给self 桨得到桨
So on line 20, we're just calling self.paddle gets paddle.
我们正在初始化一个新的paddle对象
We're initializing a new paddle object.
然后我们也在跟踪这个
And then we're keeping track of also this
就是一个简单的暂停演示
is a simple, like, pause demonstration.
如果赛尔夫停顿了一下 那么--事实上是的
If self.paused, then-- actually yeah.
我说了自我停顿吗？
Did I say self.paused?
是的
I did.
好的.
OK.
我只是没有初始化它
I just don't initialize it to anything.
我应该在这里把自己设为假的
I should have set self.paused to false here.
如果self.暂停了 我们将测试是否按下了空格
If self.paused, we're going to test to see whether we're pressing space,
如果是的话就取消暂停
and if we are, unpause it.
否则 基本上只是做同样的事情反过来
Otherwise, basically just do the same exact thing in reverse.
如果我们按空格键 暂停游戏 播放声音 等等
If we press space, pause the game, play a sound, et cetera.
在第39行 我们将调用桨的更新
Here on line 39, we're just going to call update on the paddle.
记住 测试左输入还是右输入
Which, just remember, test for left or right input.
在这里我们希望能够逃离游戏
Here we want to be able to escape the game,
所以我们会有一个负责逃跑的人
so we're going to have a handler for escape.
渲染第47行的桨 这将做爱 图形 绘制
Render the paddle on lines 47, which will do the love.graphics.draw
和我们之前看到的一样 但它会使用
with a quad as we saw before, but it'll use
皮肤和桨大小以索引到四边形瓦片片中
the skin and the size of that paddle to index into the quads tile sheet
适当地
appropriately.
然后这里如果我们暂停了 我们就画
And then here if we're paused, let's just draw
屏幕中间的一些文字写着“你好”
some text in the middle of the screen that just says Pause.
我们用大号字体
And we use the large font.
所以我们现在可以继续演示 看看所有的东西都在一起
So we can go ahead and demo this now and see everything come together.
我们像以前一样有我们的StartState
We have as before our StartState.
但是如果我们按下Enter键
But if we press Enter, now we go to our PlayState
我们在屏幕底部有一个桨
and we just have a paddle at the bottom of the screen.
是2号 1号皮
It's size two, skin one.
只有蓝色的皮肤
Just the blue skin.
我们可以像这样左右移动
And we can move it left or right like that.
如果它击中屏幕的左侧 它会停止
And if it hits the left side of the screen, it will stop.
如果它击中屏幕的右侧 它也会停止
And if it hits the right side of the screen, it will stop as well.
所以我们已经取得了进展 但这是最基本的事情之一
So we've made progress, but this is one of the fundamental things
我今天要展示的是 就像 使用四元组和分类
I'd like to showcase today is just, like, using quads and categorizing
他们 组织他们 并能够画出
them, organizing them, and being able to draw
您的资产来自一个大的汇编图像 而不是跟踪
your assets from a large compiled image rather than keep track
不管它拍下多少张照片
of however many images it would take.
你必须将它们全部命名并进行分类
And you have to name all of them and sort them.
这只会是一种巨大的痛苦
It would just be a big pain.
所以是的
So yeah.
当你有不止一个精灵的时候 肯定会继续前进
Definitely going forward when you have more than one sprite,
你想把它放在一张纸上
you want to sort of put it together in one sheet,
这就是我们实现这一目标的方法
and that's how we can accomplish that.
但我们没有砖头 这很可能是
But we don't have bricks, and this is probably
除了球拍和球之外 突破的另一个主要组成部分
the other big main component of Breakout besides the paddle and the ball.
我们想要的是我们可以在屏幕上真正击中和瞄准的砖块
We want to have bricks that we can actually hit and aim for on the screen.
因此 此次更新将解决这一问题
So this update will address that.
那么让我们继续来看看Breakout2 in Main.Lua
So let's go ahead and take a look at Breakout2 in main.lua.
我要在这里把它打开
I'm going to open it up here.
在第66行 您可以看到在我们的GFrame中有一个新的表
On line 66, you can see we have a new table in our gframes.
因为我们有一个专门用来划桨的 所以我们就拿出来了
Because we had one just for paddles, we took out
只有我们精灵床单上的球拍
just the paddles from our sprite sheet.
我们将对蛋蛋做同样的事情
We're going to do the same thing for just the balls.
所以我们要看--如果我们看这里
So we're going to look at-- if we look here,
我们可以看到 球是在这里的所有砖块之后出现的
we can see that the balls sort of come after all of the bricks here
它们只是以八个像素宽乘八个像素来布置
and they're just laid out in eight pixels wide by eight
像素高的增量在这里
pixels tall increments here.
所以四个像素对应一块砖 四个球对应一块砖
So four pixels to one brick, four balls to one brick,
两个球水平对一 然后垂直两个球
two balls to one horizontally, and then two balls vertically.
因此 我们最终要做的只是我们的实用程序中的一个简单函数
And so what we'll end up doing is just a simple function in our util
我们来看看这一点
that takes a look at that.
因此 让我们继续查看我们的util.lua 我们已经对其进行了更改
So let's go ahead and take a look at our util.lua, which we've made changes to.
所以它要做的是做同样的事情
And so what this is going to do is sort of do the same thing
就像我们以前做的那样
that we did before.
它必须迭代
It has to iterate.
所以请注意 我们有两排球
So notice we have two rows of balls.
我们有这四个 我们有这三个
We have these four and we have these three.
所以我们想要迭代四次
So we want to iterate four times.
你想知道这里的偏移量是多少
You want to find whatever the offset is here,
X和Y 所以看起来是3乘以32 然后是3乘以16
the X and Y. So it looks like three times 32 and then three times 16.
所以96乘以--
So 96 by--
我不会做数学
I can't do math.
不管16乘以3是什么
Whatever 16 times three is.
然后我们就会变成48岁
And then we'll end up 48.
然后我们会有--
And then we'll have--
这就是我们在这里所做的
which is what we do here.
所以我们有两次迭代
So we have two iterations.
所以从零到三的四个循环
So a four loop that goes from zero to three.
所以最上面的一排 四个
So the top row, the four.
我们在这里设一个柜台
We'll set a counter to one here.
还请注意96和48
And notice also 96 and 48.
这是我们设定的X和Y
That's the X and the Y that we're setting.
这就是各个球精灵的偏移量
That's where the offset is for the individual ball sprites.
柜台的四人组--
Quads at counter gets--
请注意 四边形还有一张桌子
and notice also quads is a table.
我们要把这个退掉
We're going to return this.
在柜台的四人组得到了爱
Quads at counter gets love.graphics.newquad at X, Y.
八个像素宽 八个像素高
Eight pixels wide, eight pixels tall.
这就是球的大小
That's how large the balls are.
然后我们再加8 因为我们要向右转
And then we're going to add eight to it because we're going to the right.
所以这个迭代是从左到右的
So this iteration just goes left to right.
然后在这里 我们将基本上将X设置为96
And then here we're going to do basically X being set to 96
然后Y变为56
and then Y to 56.
然后因为我们直接在这里编辑X
And then because we were editing X directly in here,
我们希望将X重置为96 但也要添加
we want to reset X back to 96, but then also add
8个像素 这样我们就有了下一行的起点
the eight pixels so that we have the start for the next row
纵向上 56日元也是如此
vertically, so at Y 56.
在这里做完全相同的事情 但只做
Do the exact same thing here, but only do it
三次 因为回想一下 上面有四个球
three times because recall there is four balls on top
然后是底部的三个球
and then three balls on bottom.
然后在最后还回来
And then return it at the very end.
所以现在我们只有一张单独的桌子
And so now we have just an individual table.
我们不需要像一张巨大的四边形餐桌一样
We don't need to keep like one monstrous table of quads,
我觉得这有点杂乱无章
which I find sort of disorganized.
我们可以只有一张划桨架的桌子
We can just have a table of frames for the paddles,
还有球 还有我们将会看到的砖头
and the balls, and the bricks as we'll see.
实际上 我想我把它放在这里了
Actually, I have it up here I think.
也许不会
Maybe not.
所以在舞会上--哦 实际上 等等
So in ball-- oh, actually, hold on.
抱歉的
Sorry.
所以我们在看--
So we were looking at--
我不小心跳过了这一条
I skipped over this one on accident.
所以弹跳更新
So the bounce update.
所以我刚才说的每件事都是相关的 但我不小心
So everything I just said is relevant, but I accidentally
向右打了两下
hit that right two times.
我们想要转到退回更新 因为这稍微简单一些
We want to go to the bounce update because this is slightly simpler.
所以我们只是在谈论球 这太完美了
So we were just talking about the ball, which is perfect.
所以我们要拿着球 然后我们要把它添加到场景中
So we're going to take the ball and then we're going to add that to the scene,
我们要做的就是从墙上跳起来
and we're just going to implement bouncing off the walls.
所以实际上 与代码几乎完全相同
So actually, pretty identical to the code
我们看到了Pong 你只需要检测球是否有
we saw for Pong where you just detect whether the ball has
超出屏幕的左、右或上边缘
gone past the left, right, or top edge of the screen.
在这种情况下 它还将允许我们转到屏幕底部
In this case, it will also allow us to go to the bottom of the screen
我们还将实现与球拍的碰撞
and we'll also implement colliding with the paddle
那么 你就可以感受到真正的游戏效果 以及那种感觉
so then get a sense of the actual game play and what that feels like.
所以目前一切都是最新的
So everything is currently current.
所以我们要去--
So we're going to go--
在谈到实际拿到个人球的功能后
after talking about the function to actually get the individual ball
从电子表格中拿出四元组 我们要
quads out of the spreadsheet, we're going
来看看球类 它将允许我们在场景中产生它们
to look at the ball class which is going to allow us to spawn them in our scene.
所以球的宽度和高度都是8
So a ball takes a width and height of eight.
没有速度
No velocity.
但我们将允许我们自己使用皮肤来初始化球
But we're going to allow ourselves to initialize the ball with the skin,
我们稍后会看到这是一个可爱的小东西给你
and we'll see this later just as a cutesy little thing to you
使用实际的单个精灵 而不只是一个恒定的精灵
use the actual individual sprites rather than just one constant sprite.
我们只会给它一个介于1和7之间的随机数
We're just going to give it a random number between one and seven
因为有七个四边形
because there are seven quads.
然后我们将只使用格框、球和数学点随机数
And then we'll just use gframes balls and math dot random number
才能得到我们想要的真正的球面
to get the actual ball spread that we want.
所以我们在球内有一个简单的碰撞函数
And so we have a simple collides function within ball
这将允许我们检查是否与某个物体相撞
that would allow us to check to see whether we've collided with something
它具有X、Y宽度和高度
that has a X, Y width and a height.
所以这是一个简单的A B碰撞检测
So it's a simple A, B collision detection.
然后在这里我们有重置
And then here we have reset.
只需将其重置到屏幕中央即可
Just resets it to the middle of the screen.
更新应用速度
Update applies velocity.
我们已经看过的东西
Stuff we've already seen.
这就是我们真正实现弹离墙壁的地方
This is where we actually implement bouncing off the walls.
因此 如果X小于或等于零 则大于
So if X is less than or equal to zero, greater than
或等于虚拟宽度减8 或小于或等于零
or equal to virtual width minus eight, or less than or equal to zero,
这应该是我们反转速度的地方
this should be where we reverse the velocity.
在它从左侧反弹的情况下 我们想要反转X速度
In the case of it bouncing off the left side, we want to reverse the X velocity
但要继续往上走
but keep it going up.
如果它击中顶部 那么我们想要反转
If it hits the top, then we want to reverse
Y速度 以保持它朝任何方向移动
the Y velocity to keep it moving in whatever direction it was moving.
右手边的墙也是这样
And same thing with the right hand wall.
然后播放一段墙壁上的热门音乐
And then play a wall hit sound.
我们在今天的节目中融入了这些声音
And we're incorporating the sounds sort of as we go today
就因为它们太简单了
just because they're so simple.
仅仅得到一点反馈也是很好的
And it's also kind of nice just to have a little bit of feedback
当你实际上是游戏的终点时
when you're actually endpoint of the game.
这里的绘图代码与此完全相同
And the exact same code is here for drawing.
所以我们有主纹理 但现在我们使用的是GFrame球
So we have main texture, but now we're using gframes balls,
然后我们在self.kin上对其进行索引
and then we're indexing that at self.skin.
回想一下 我们刚刚在这里设置了self.kin
And recall that we just set self.skin in here.
所以我们要做的就是把它随机
So all we need to do to just make it random
就是在我们创造一个新球的任何地方 给它一个数学运算
is just wherever we create a new ball, just give it a math.random7,
然后 它将索引到那个四元表中
and then that will index into that quads table
这样我们每次都可以画出不同的球纹理
so we can draw a different ball texture each time.
所以让我们继续下去 看看--
And so let's go ahead and see--
哦 事实上 不是的
oh, actually, no.
我们需要关注的最后一件事是PlayState
And one last thing we need to look at is the PlayState
也有一些新的代码
has a little bit of new code as well.
我们要生一个球 所以这就是我们要做的
We're going to spawn a ball, so this is where we do it here.
我不是随机做的 但如果我想的话 我可以在这里随机做
I'm not doing it random, but I could do it random here if I wanted to.
我可以算术 随机7 而且每次我们启动的时候
I could math.random7, and every time we boot up
这个游戏将会是不同的颜色 因为它
the game it's going to be a different color because it's
将会是一张不同的皮肤
going to be a different skin.
我们需要更新一下球
We need to update the ball.
因此 在第50行 我们只需更新它 就像我们处理划桨一样
So on line 50 we just update it like we do the paddle.
然后在第52行 我们只是测试一下
And then on line 52, we're just testing to see
它是否与球拍相撞 因为我们只用了简单的A
whether it collides with the paddle because we're using just simple A,
如果它与球拍相撞 我们就可以假定它正在坠落
A, B, B. If it collides with the paddle, we can assume it was coming down.
我们可以反转为增量Y
We can just reverse as delta Y.
现在 有谁知道什么可能是当前的问题
Now, does anybody know what might be a current issue
该函数的当前实现情况如何？
with the current implementation of this function?
尤其是这条线
Particularly with this line.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：会的
COLTON OGDEN: It will.
你走上了正确的道路
You're on the right track.
答案是 如果球是从侧面传来的
The answer was, if the ball is coming from the side,
它不一定会在正确的Y方向反弹回来
it won't necessarily be bounced back up in the right Y direction.
如果它是从侧面来的 在这种情况下 它总是
If it's coming from the side, it will always, in this case,
是从上面来的
be coming from up above.
因此 在右增量Y中 它总是在倒转
So it always still be reversing in the right delta Y.
但如果它以一个角度进入会发生什么
But what's going to happen if it comes in at an angle
然后基本上不是重置了吗？
and then isn't basically reset?
就像现在 如果它从一个角度来 它
Like right now if it comes at an angle and it
被抓到了--比方说它就像是在桨的顶端下方
gets caught-- let's say it's like below the top edge of the paddle.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：你会有一个无限的碰撞
COLTON OGDEN: You're going to get an infinite collision
循环 因为我们没有重置它的位置
loop because we're not resetting it's position,
我们只是在更新它的速度
we're only updating its velocity.
如果它从侧面以正确的角度进入
If it comes in at the right angle from the side,
它会卡在球拍里
it's going to get stuck inside the paddle
然后 它会导致一些时髦的行为
and then it's going to cause a little bit of funky behavior.
我会试着在我的演示中实现这一点
I'll try and see if I can make that happen in my demonstration here.
但这就是所有这些更新的要点
But that's the gist of all of these updates.
因此 如果我们开始 我们可以立即看到我们有一个球
So if we go to Start, we can see immediately we have a ball.
当它撞到侧面或顶部时 它会相应地反弹
And when it hits the sides or the top, it bounces accordingly.
它击中了球拍
It hits the paddle.
因此 当它从顶部进入时 它会翻转Y速度
So when it comes in from the top flush on the top, it flips the Y velocity.
让我们看看我能不能从这个角度拍到它
Let's see if I can get it at an angle here.
这就是了
There it is.
它会卡住的
It'll get stuck.
所以每当你进行A、A、B、B碰撞检测时
And so whenever you sort of do A, A, B, B collision detection,
只要记住总是重置它的位置就行了
just remember to always reset the position of whatever it
它是被碰撞的 正在移动的 所以它不会卡住
is that collided that's moving so that it doesn't clip
一次又一次地被困在别的东西里
and get stuck inside of something else over and over again.
是
Yes.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是我一直在做爱情空间点
COLTON OGDEN: The question is I'm always doing love space dot,
而不是仅仅使用
and as opposed to just running things from using
任何文件的完整路径 为了做到这一点--您也是
the complete path of whatever the file is, in order to do that-- so are you
在Mac还是Windows机器上？
on a Mac or a Windows machine?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：所以在Windows系统上 这就有点棘手了
COLTON OGDEN: So on a Windows machine it is a little trickier,
但我已经找到了一种非常好的VS代码插件
but I've found a really nice sort of plug-in for VS Code.
因此 如果您使用的是VS Code 这是我使用的编辑器 它有插件
So if you're VS Code, which is the editor that I use, it has plug-ins
你可以下载的其中一个插件是Love2D
and one of the plug-ins that you can download is for Love2D
它有一个配置 如果你只需按下Alt L
and it has a config where if you just press Alt L,
它将运行您当前所在目录
it will run whatever directory you're currently in,
无论你目前参与的是什么项目
whatever project you're currently in.
它将呼唤爱
It will call Love.
它会为你把它添加到你的道路上
It adds it to your path for you.
因此 如果您想让它工作 请下载VS代码上的Love2D插件
So download the Love2D plug-in on VS code if you want that to work.
我在Mac上 所以我可以编辑我的批次配置文件
I'm on a Mac, so I can edit what's called my batch profile,
并将其别名Love添加到我文件系统中的完整路径
and alias Love to its complete path in my file system.
你也可以做同样的事情--
And you can do the same thing with--
我不知道Windows在别名方面是如何工作的
I don't know how it would work with Windows in terms of aliasing,
但从本质上讲 这与输入通向爱的整个道路是一样的
but it's essentially the same thing as typing out the entire path to Love,
不过 我要换个词
but only I'm changing it to another word.
我要把它改成爱
I'm changing it to Love.
所以我将Love设置为应用程序斜杠
So I'm setting Love equals to application slash
Love.app/内容/资源等
love.app/content/resources et cetera.
问得好
So good question.
我会在Windows上下载
I would download on Windows.
我是VS Code和Love2D插件的铁杆粉丝
I'm a big fan of VS Code and the Love2D plug-in.
我建议你调查一下这个问题
I would recommend looking into that.
我相信还有其他插件 还有一个页面
And I'm sure there are other plug-ins, and there's a page also
在网站上--
on the website--
我目前没有打开浏览器
I don't have a browser open at the moment.
但在维基上 你可以看到入门页面
But on the wiki, you can look at the Getting Started page.
我相信这就像是love2d.com/wiki/gettingstarted
I believe it's like love2d.com/wiki/gettingstarted.
他们有一堆不同操作的说明
They have a bunch of instructions for different operating
允许您进行排序的系统和不同的文本编辑器
systems and different text editors that allow you to get sort
更高效的工作流程
of a more efficient workflow going.
还有其他问题吗？
So any other questions?
好的
All right.
所以我们做了弹跳更新
So we did the bounce update.
现在我们终于可以编辑砖块了
Now we can finally edit the bricks.
我要说的是 再加上砖头
Add in the bricks, I should say.
所以这些都很简单
So these are pretty simple.
所以我们要来看看它
So we're going to take a look at it.
现在我们不会做任何花哨的程序世代
And right now we're not going to do any sort of fancy procedural generation,
我们只是要在屏幕上放几块砖
we're just going to get some bricks on the screen.
只是一些简单的砖块
Just some easy bricks.
或者更确切地说 我们将得到一些非常基本的程序性生成
Or rather, we will get some very basic procedural generation,
但不会达到我们很快就会看到的水平
but not to the level that we'll see soon.
我们很快就会看到这一点
We'll see that very soon.
好的
OK.
所以我要进入我的主 Lua在这里
So I'm going to go into my main.lua here.
我要进入《越狱3》
I'm going to go into the Breakout3.
和我们之前在第67行做的相同的事情
And same thing that we did before on line 67,
我们的框架里只有一张新的砖桌
we just have a new bricks table in our gframes.
它只会产生四边形的砖块
And it just generate quads bricks.
我们从util.lua调用 所以我们也可以快速查看它
We call from util.lua, so we can look at that really quick as well.
这个其实很简单
This one's actually really easy.
Sourceutil.Lua
Sourceutil.lua.
因为它们从屏幕的最顶端开始
Because they start at the very top of the screen,
我们可以假设--我们可以有效地
we can assume that-- we could effectively
把这整件事当做是这些
treat this whole thing as if it were just these
并且只生成宽度和高度恒定的四边形
and just generate quads at a constant width and height
因为 实际上 我们只需要正在生成的帧的一个子集
because, effectively, we only need a subset of the frames that's generating.
因为它是这样产生它们的 从上到下 从左到右
Because it's generating them this way, top to bottom, left to right,
我们可以一直抓取到这里 用
we can just grab all the way up to here using
表 切片 我们之前看到的 而不是
table.slice, which we saw before, and not
担心索引到任何奇怪的 比如
worry about indexing into any weird, like,
具有需要按顺序编制索引的任何常量X和Y
having any constants X and Y that we need to index with in order
以获得补偿
to get an offset.
我们可以做一个非常简单的--
We can just do a very simple--
如果我们往下到第57行 生成四块砖 它只做一张表 切片
if we go down to line 57, generate quads bricks, it just does a table.slice.
在此基础上 我们将生成四元地图集32 16
And so within that, we're going to generate quads atlas 32,16.
这将产生将我们的精灵工作表除以32的效果
So this is going to have the effect of dividing up our sprite sheet by 32
以16块为单位
by 16 pieces.
它会很好地产生所有这些
It's going to generate all of these just fine,
但它会在这里 这里有四个四边形
but then it's going to have quads here, here, here, here, here
与你在这里看到的四边形不对齐
that don't line up with the quads that you see here
因为它只是盲目地假设那张纸上的所有精灵
because it's just blindly assuming that all of the sprites in that sheet
都是一样的大小 因为这就是我们要做的
are the same size because that's all we're doing.
我们只是调用生成四元组 如果您还记得的话
We're just calling generate quads, which if you recall,
只是在我们的整个地图集中生成固定大小的宽度和高度
just generates a fixed size width and height throughout our entire atlas,
这对于许多对称的床单来说是很棒的
which is great for a lot of sheets that are symmetrical,
但在某些情况下 比如在这里
but there are cases where we have, like, for example here, where
我们的电子表格是不对称的
our spreadsheet is asymmetrical.
我们有不同大小的球拍 我们有
We have paddles of differing sizes, we have
八乘八的球 我们有砖头
the balls which are eight by eight, we have the bricks,
我们在底部有其他加电装置
we have the other power ups at the bottom.
但生成的四边形砖块占据了那张桌子
But the generate quads bricks takes in that table
我们正在生成的 这将是一堆帧
that we're generating, which is going to be a bunch of frames
这是我们不想要的
that we don't want.
他们中的许多人剪掉了 一半剪掉了
Many of them clipped, half clipped.
然后我们就把它从1变为21
And then we're just going to take it from one to 21.
当我们这样做的时候 1到21实际上是--这就是这些
And when we do that, one to 21 is effectively-- that's how many of these
确实有
there are.
所以是18 然后是1 2 3
So 18 and then one, two, three.
所以从1到21 所有这些都是
So from one to 21, all of those.
这将是所有的砖
That will be all the bricks.
我们可以扔掉所有剩下的四边形
We can throw away all the rest of the quads
然后盲目地假设它们都是一样大小的
and just blindly assume that they're all the same size.
那么 对于四元组如何工作或这些桌子是如何工作的 有什么问题吗？
So any questions on how quads or how any of these tables are working?
好的
OK.
所以我们要继续下去
So we're going to go ahead.
我们现在有一个新的班级 布里克·卢亚
We have a new class now, brick.lua.
如此简单的积木
So simple building blocks.
在第30行的brick.lua中 我们有一面名为in play的旗帜
In brick.lua on line 30, we have a flag called in play.
自我陶醉成真
self.inplay gets true.
所以我们只需要用这个来渲染
And so we're just going to use this to render.
我们只想说 如果它在起作用 就渲染它
We're just going to say, if it's in play, render it.
如果不是 则不要呈现它
If it's not, don't render it.
就这么简单
It's that simple.
这样我们就不必担心对象重新分配或任何花哨的事情了
That way we don't have to worry about object deallocation or anything fancy.
我们已经准备好了所有的砖块 以及它是否正在发挥作用
We have all of our bricks and whether it's in play
或者不是 呈现它或执行更新逻辑
or not, render it or perform update logic.
如果它不存在 就假装它不存在
And if it's not in play, just pretend it doesn't exist.
忽略它就好
Just ignore it.
我们只会有30人 或者我不知道有多少人
We're only going to have like 30 or I don't know how many,
在我们的场景中 一次最多13 x 4块砖 所以担心内存释放
13 max by four bricks in our scene at once, so worrying about freeing memory
其实并不是什么问题
isn't really an issue.
但是如果你有一百万种不同的东西一直在产生
But if you have a million different things getting generated all the time,
在游戏中拥有简单可能并不总是错误的
having simple in play is false might not always
这是可行的 因为您需要存储所有这些对象的所有内存
be viable because you need to store all that memory for all those objects.
所以这里只是一条捷径 但不一定是最好的
So just a shortcut here, but not necessarily best
为大型比赛做练习
practice for very large games.
但对于小游戏来说 这无疑是既好又简单的
But certainly great and simple for small games.
在第37行 我们定义了一个名为Brick Hit的函数
On line 37, we define a function called brick hit.
所有这些都只是播放音效 并将其设置为假
And all this does is just play a sound effect and set in play to false.
所以我们要做的就是检查
And so all we're going to do is just check
来查看是否存在冲突 然后调用此Hit函数
to see whether there's a collision and then just call this hit function,
播放一个声音 然后假装它不再存在
play a sound, and then just pretend it doesn't exist anymore.
然后渲染 渲染所做的就是如果它正在播放 检查正在播放的标志
And then render, all render does is if it's in play, check the in play flag,
在砖块处绘制Main 或使用我们创建的砖桌
draw main at bricks or using our bricks table here that we created.
然后我们从一点开始 然后
And then we're going to start at one and then
我们将根据我们的颜色减去1乘以4来索引它
we're going to index it based on our color minus one times four,
然后我们要添加它的层
and then we're going to add it's tier.
所以 如果你还记得的话 有一 二 三 四
So there are, if you recall, one, two, three, four,
五种颜色 四个层次
five colors and four tiers.
所以我们要做的是在不同的颜色之间跳跃
And so what we're going to do is we're going to jump between the colors.
所以我们会得到值1 值2 值3 值4 值5
So we'll go value one, value two, value three, value four, value five.
这将是我们的前五个 或者我想是六个
That will be our first five or I guess six.
这将是我们的头六块砖
That will be our first six bricks.
然后我们将开始一 二 三--或者我们将添加
And then we're going to go one, two, three-- or we're going to add,
我们基本上会有一个层次
we're going to have a tier basically.
可能是一、二、三或四
It'll be one, two, three, or four.
如果是在第一级 那么我们可以添加--
And if it's at tier one, then we can just add--
基本上是索引到我们所在的任何一层
basically to index into whatever tier we're on,
无论我们的索引是什么 我们只需添加减一级即可
we just need to add tier minus one to whatever our index is.
所以在这里 如果我们的层是一层 那么我们只想渲染这个块
So here if our tier is one, then we just want to render this block.
我们不想去下一家
We don't want to go to the next one.
所以我们就说一级减去一级
So we're just going to say tier minus one.
我们将添加--
We're going to add--
所以一减一等于零
so one minus one is zero.
所以我们从零开始 明白这一点
So we're going at zero to this, get this.
但如果是第二级 我们会增加一级、二级和三级
But if tiers two, we'll add one, and two, and three.
然后我们只需将我们想要的任何砖乘以我们的颜色
And then we just multiply whatever brick we want by our color.
将它乘以4 就可以得到我们实际颜色的偏移量
Multiply it by four to get an offset for whatever our actual color is.
所以我们选择我们的颜色 找出它在床单上的位置
So we take our color, figure out where on the sheet it is,
然后只需将我们的层添加到其中 以便为其编制索引
and then just add our tier to it in order to index
添加到我们的电子表格中
into our spreadsheet accordingly.
这就是数学所要做的
And so that's what the math here is doing.
如果我们回到PlayState--
And if we go back to our PlayState--
我要开始走得更快一点
and I'm going to start moving a little bit faster
这样我们就能跟上进度了
just so we can keep caught up.
但在我们的PlayState中 我们在这里注意到一件事
But in our PlayState, one thing that we notice here,
我们看到了一个名为Level Maker的新班级
we have a new class called level maker that we're seeing,
这是一个名为createmap的函数
which was a function called createmap.
我们将去掉所有产生我们的关卡的逻辑
We're going to take out all the logic for generating our levels
我们只需要把它放在一个地方
and we're just going to put it in one place.
我们要给那个关卡制造者打电话
We're going to call that level maker.
而不是在我们不同的州 也许
Rather than in our different states that maybe
生成像PlayState或I一样的积木
generate the bricks like the PlayState or I
我猜应该是ServeState VictoryState
guess it would be the ServeState, VictoryState,
我猜 而不是产生所有的砖
I guess, rather than generating all the bricks
在其固有代码状态下 让我们创建一个关卡标记器
in that state within it's innate code, let's just make a level maker
我们可以说 好的 把砖放到平地上 创建地图
and we can just say, OK, set bricks to levelmaker.createmap,
这将返回一张桌子的砖块
which will return a table of bricks.
抱歉 逻辑和我们之前看到的一样
Same-- excuse me-- logic as we saw before.
在本例中 我们将迭代k Brick
In this case, we're just going to iterate for k brick
成对的自家的砖块
in pairs of self.bricks.
如果砖块在比赛中发生碰撞 如果球与之相撞
If the brick's in play and it collides, if the ball collides with it,
然后击打它 这将使它不再发挥作用
then hit it, which will set it not into play.
很简单的A A B B
So simple A, A, B, B.
最后 我们这里有我们的呈现逻辑
And then lastly, we have our render logic here,
它会把那张砖头桌子拿来 然后迭代
which is going to take that bricks table and just iterate over it.
我们最不应该看到的就是
And the last thing we should probably look at
是真正的关卡制造者本身 在这种情况下很简单
is the actual level maker itself, which in this case is very simple,
但我们稍后会看到 它会变得更复杂
but we'll see it gets a little bit more complicated later when we do it.
当我们有一个更详细的程序性生成方法来处理我们的级别时
When we have a more elaborate procedural generation approach to our levels.
但现在 我们只需要在这里设置两个随机变量
But right now, we're just going to say set two random variables here.
行数和列数
Number of rows and columns.
然后对于每行或基本上每行和每列
And then for every row or for basically every row and every column,
创建一块新砖
create a new brick.
然后这里有一些数学问题
And then there's some math here.
我会略读一下 但基本上
I'm going to kind of skim over it, but basically it
计算砖块的位置 然后给我们
calculates where the brick is and then gives us
两边各有八个像素的填充
eight pixels of padding on either side.
然后根据它的数量 它需要将所有
And then based on how many it is, it needs to center all
然后把砖向左移动一定的量
the bricks and shift them by a certain amount to the left
然后开始把它们都画出来
and then start drawing all of them.
这就是这段代码在这里的基本功能
And that's essentially what this code does here.
所以计算中心
So calculate the center.
我在这里的评论中写下了 但我要去
I wrote it out in comments here, but I'm going
只是暂时不去想它
just kind of glaze over it for now.
但实际上 把所有的砖块放在中间
But effectively, center all the bricks.
基本上计算什么样的偏移量在X轴上你需要把所有的人
Basically calculate what offset on the X-axis you need to put all of them
让它们看起来居中 然后把它们都画出来
so that they appear centered, and then you're going to draw them all out.
这就是水平仪制造者课程的内容
And then that's it for the level maker class.
所以简单的行数和列数 然后用砖块填满一个表
So simply number of rows and columns, and then fill a table with bricks
但是把它们的X设为我们需要的
but set their X equal to however much we need to center all
当他们都被拉出来的时候
of them when they're all drawn out.
所以我们需要计算 我们需要基本上把我们的列数
So we need to figure, we need to basically take in our number of columns
在我们这样做的时候
into account when we do that.
然后如果我们进入Breakout3并运行它 我们就有了砖块
And then if we go into Breakout3 and run that, we have bricks.
它们会被撞上 一旦它们被撞上
They're getting collided with, and as soon as they get hit,
碰撞在这些砖块中的每一个都被设置为假
collided are in play on each of those bricks gets set to false
它们不再被渲染
and they no longer get rendered.
它们不再更新碰撞方面
And they no longer get updated in terms of collision.
现在 我们仍然有问题的球没有得到重置
Now, we still have the issue with the ball not getting reset.
我们会解决的
We'll fix that.
很容易搞定
That's an easy fix.
但我们已经走了很远了
But we're coming a long way.
我们的进展相当快
We have things moving at quite a pace.
我将继续前进 并移动到下一个代码位
I'm going to go ahead and move to the next bit of code here.
这是另一段代码
So this is another bit of code.
我会在这里稍微忽略一些细节
I'm going to sort of glaze over a little bit of the details here.
但在高层次上 我们需要做的是
But at a high level what we need to do is it's one thing
来检测我们是否撞上了一块砖头
to detect that we've collided with a brick,
但在《越狱》里 球会从砖块上弹开
but in Breakout, the ball bounces off of the brick
这取决于它击中的是哪一边
depending on which side it hits.
我们不能仅仅根据碰撞就知道这一点
And we don't know this necessarily just based off of the collision.
我们只知道碰撞是真是假
We just know whether the collision is true or not.
我们不知道它从哪里来 也不知道它与多少物体相撞
We don't know where it came from and how much it collided with.
然后我们还要固定我们的桨
And then we're also going to fix our paddles so that rather than-- because
目前它所做的只是否定Y速度
currently all it does is just negate whatever the Y velocity is,
但我们想增加一点变化
but we want to add a little bit more variety
当我们打球的时候
to how we end up sort of ricocheting the ball off the paddle when we play
这样我们就能制定一点策略
so that we can sort of strategize a little bit,
给我们自己一点游戏的机会
give ourselves a little bit of game play.
所以 如果我们向右移动 我们碰到了水坑的右边
So if we are moving to the right and we hit the right edge of the puddle
有了球 它可能会朝着更锋利的方向前进
with the ball, it should probably go in a sharper direction.
左边也是一样
Same thing with the left side.
而我们可以通过选择中间部分来有效地做到这一点
And we can effectively do that by taking the middle,
计算出它离中心有多远
figuring out how far away from the center it is,
然后在负或正的方向上放大我们的增量X
and then just amplifying our delta X in the negative or positive direction
在此基础上
based off of that.
而这会导致这种情况的发生
And that has the effect of causing that to happen.
所以在这里我们可以看到我们的球有点像是在划桨
So here we can see we have the ball sort of coming at the paddle,
让我们假设球拍正在向左移动
and let's pretend that the paddle is moving to the left.
在这种情况下 无论球离中心有多远
In this case, however far away the ball is from the center,
我们希望按一定的比例进行调整 然后
we want to scale that by some amount and then
最终使它成为负的增量X 因为这实际上是
end up making that our negative delta X, because that's effectively
这个游戏通常是怎么运作的
how the game normally works.
如果你把球拍向左或向右移动
If you move the paddle to the left or the right,
在拐角或其他什么地方击球 给它一个尖锐的角度
hit it on a corner or something, gives it that sharp angle.
而这实际上就是尖锐的角度
And that's effectively what the sharp angle is.
它只是一个很强的增量X 并且它被放大得越大
It's just a strong delta X, and it gets amplified the larger this is.
所以基本上就是把这个 乘以某个数值
So just basically take this, multiply it by some amount,
然后在你的DX上设置为负值或正值
and then make it negative or positive on your dx.
这就是你的划桨碰撞V2
That's your sort of paddle collision V2.
砖块碰撞有点--
Brick collision is a little bit--
这很简单 但有点复杂
it's pretty simple, but it's a little bit more complicated.
基本上 我们需要做的就是检查一下 看看球的哪边
Basically what we need to do is just check and see which edge of the ball
不在砖头里面
isn't inside the brick.
所以如果左边的边缘--我们也可以
And so if the left edge of the-- and we can also sort of
稍微简化一下
simplify this a little bit.
如果左边--就像你在这里看到的伪代码--
If the left-- as you see here by the pseudocode--
如果球的左边缘在砖外并且DX为正
if the left edge of the ball is outside the brick and the dx is positive,
然后我们可以说 哦 我们基本上可以假设
then we can say, oh, we can basically assume
我们是从左边进来的 所以我们应该
we've come in from the left side, so we should probably
在左侧朝相反的Y方向行驶
go in the opposite Y direction on the left side.
或者很抱歉 我们应该朝同一个Y方向前进 但要取消我们的增量
Or sorry, we should go in the same Y direction, but negate our delta
因为我们是从左边进来的
X. Because we're coming in from the left,
左边在砖块外面 所以把它弹回来
the left side is outside the brick, so bounce it back.
同样的道理也适用于右边
And the same thing for the right edge.
我们只做这个测试 球的左边 如果dx是正数
And we only do this test, the left edge of the ball, if dx is positive.
因为如果DX是负值 就不可能
Because if dx is negative, there's no way
球撞到了我们的砖的左侧
the ball's colliding with the left side of our brick.
所以我们可以有效地走捷径
So we can shortcut that effectively.
我们在这里做同样的逻辑 只是在正确的边缘
We do the same exact logic here, just on the right edge
而不是左边的边缘
of the brick instead of the left edge.
如果这些都不成立 我们就会
And then if none of those hold true, we're
去看看球的顶边是否在砖头的顶边之上
going to see if the top edge of the ball is above the top edge of the brick.
如果是这样的话 我们知道我们是从顶端开始的
And if that's the case, we know that we've hit from the top.
我们可以触发顶部碰撞
We can trigger a top collision.
如果这些都不成立 我们知道
And if none of those have held true, we know
我们发生了某种碰撞
that we have had a collision of some kind,
我们可以只登记一次底部碰撞
we can just register a bottom collision.
所以这是这个排序的一个简单版本
And so this is a simple version of this sort
做突破碰撞的方式
of way of doing Breakout collision.
它在弯道方面有一些缺陷
It has a few faults when it comes to corners,
有时弯道可能有点挑剔
sometimes corners can be a little bit finicky,
但我要说的是 它99%的情况下都是有效的
but I would say it works 99% of the time.
要获得一个更健壮、更好的示例 我将查看以下URL
For a much more robust and a better example, I would look at this URL
这是因为他也陷入了全面的崩溃
here because he also goes into a full sort of breakdown
他将如何实施阿卡诺德 这是同样的事情有效地
of how he would implement arkanoid, which is the same thing effectively
如果你只是想从另一个角度看它 那就作为突破口
as Breakout if you just want an alternative look at it.
但基本上 他的解决方案包括取X和Y的多少
But basically, his solution involved taking how much the X and the Y
在砖块相对于球的不同点上有所不同
differed on different points of the bricks relative to the ball.
我相信他也把球当做一个有中心点的真正的球
And I believe he also kept the ball as an actual ball with a center point,
尽管他把它渲染成了一个长方形
even though he rendered it as a rectangle.
所以它更坚固了一点
So it's a little bit more robust.
我决定以一种更简单的方式实现它 我将展示这一点
I decided to implement it a simpler way, which I'll showcase,
这就是我演示的方式 因为它工作得很好
which is the way that I demonstrated because it worked well
这并不是太多的代码 几乎看不出来
and it wasn't too much code to sort of look over.
但我鼓励你去看看这一点
But I do encourage you to take a look at that.
我们将在《突破4》中看看我们的PlayState
We're going to look at our PlayState now in Breakout4.
在我们的PlayState中 我们将看到--
And in our PlayState, we're going to see--
抱歉的
sorry.
65行
Line 65.
这就是影响球的增量X的实际球拍代码
So this is the actual paddle code for influencing the ball's delta X.
所以基本上 如果球x小于球桨x加上它的宽度
So basically, if the ball.x is less than the paddle.x plus it's width divided
两个人 所以基本上在划桨的左边
by two, so basically on the left side of the paddle,
划桨的增量X小于零 这意味着它在向左移动--
and the paddle's delta X is less than zero, which means it's moving left--
因为我们真的不想影响它 如果我们只是
because we don't really want to necessarily influence it if we're just
原地踏步--
standing still--
我们要做我之前描述过的事情
we're going to do what I described earlier.
我们要给它一些定标器 比如一些起始值
We're going to give it some scaler, like some start off value.
在这种情况下 负50只是在某种程度上播种 给它
In this case, negative 50 is just sort of seeding this, giving it
某种初值
some sort of initial value.
然后我们只需从中点减去球的X
And then we're just going to subtract the ball's X from the middle point.
这是划桨的中点
This being the middle point of the paddle
然后再乘以8
And then just multiply it by eight.
所以不管球的X和中间有什么不同
So whatever the difference is between the ball's X and the middle
划桨的数乘以八
of the paddle, multiply it by eight.
把它加到负50 然后再求反
Add it to negative 50 and then negate that.
同时否定该整数值 从而使整个整数值变为负值
Also negate that whole value so that the whole entire value becomes negative.
因此 我们得到了更清晰的增量X 这取决于哪个角度
And we, therefore, get a sharper delta X depending on which angle
它正在到来 也是以多快的速度--
it's coming at, and also how fast--
或者不是速度有多快 而是我们是否在向左移动
or not how fast, but whether or not we are moving left.
右边也是一样的东西
And it's the exact same thing on the right side.
只是因为我们要学这个数学 这个self.paddle.x
Only because we're taking this math, this self.paddle.x
加上自拍宽度除以2减去球宽x
plus self.paddle.width divided by two minus the ball.x,
Ball.x不会大于那个点
the ball.x isn't going to be greater than that point.
所以这个值实际上是负值
So this value is actually going to be negative.
所以我们只需要用Math.abs来证明这一点
So we're going to just make it positive with math.abs.
所以绝对值
So absolute value.
只是一个Lua函数
Just a lua function.
所以球与球之间的差值的绝对值
So the absolute value of the difference between the ball's
X和中间点乘以8 加到50
X and the middle point times eight, add it to 50,
这将给我们一个正值 它的大小取决于
and that'll give us a positive value that scales depending on whether or not
我们打到了中间 我们打到了桨的右边
we've hit the middle of the, we've hit the right edge of the paddle
正在向右移动
and are moving to the right.
所以 简而言之 这就是我们如何让碰撞与划桨一起工作
And so that's, in a nutshell, how we get that collision to work with the paddle
以及我们如何将增量X调整得更大一些
and how we can tweak delta X to be scaled a little bit more
而不只是一个常量 你知道的 负数或其他什么
than just a constant, you know, negative or whatever
它是当前的x 但是是负的dy
it's current X was, but negative dy.
稍微复杂一点
A little bit more complicated.
然后是砖块的实际碰撞代码
And then the actual collision code for the bricks
它们将在这里的for循环中发生
themselves is going to take place in a for loop here.
因此 如果它在比赛中 如果球与它相撞 就击打它
So if it's in play, if the ball collides with it, hit it.
所以我加了加二
So I added plus two.
所以数学的要点是 如果bal.x小于brick.x
So the gist of the math is if ball.x is less than brick.x
球向右移动 self.ball.dx大于零
and the ball is moving to the right, self.ball.dx is greater than zero,
然后将其翻转为X速度
then flip it's X velocity.
所以把它弹到左边
So bounce it to the left.
这张支票就是这么回事
That's what this check is.
但它在角球上打得有点粗糙
But it plays a little bit rough with corners
因为从理论上讲 你可以进入一个
because you could theoretically get into a position
你以一个角度进入 它是相交的
where you come in at an angle and it's intersecting
将球拍放在两个位置 都在顶部和左侧
with the paddle in two positions, both on top and the left
或者在底部和左边
or on bottom and the left.
因此 在这种情况下 添加两个将确定命中的Y的优先顺序
So in that case, adding two sort of prioritizes the Y being hit.
所以它基本上是从球的展开式到X加2的检查
So it basically takes the check from the exposition of the ball to the X plus 2.
因此 它最终修复了一些角落 但它的要点是
And so it ends up fixing the corners a little bit, but the gist of it
只需检查Ball.x是否小于brick.x
is just check to see if the ball.x is less than the brick.x.
如果是这样 并且我们检测到了碰撞 我们可以将其弹回
And if it is and we've detected a collision, we can bounce it.
在没有加上这个加二的情况下 有一些微妙的角落问题
There are some subtle corner case bugs without adding this plus two,
所以我们加上了这一点
so we add that.
然后在这里反转速度
And then flip the velocity here.
哦 这个班次
Oh, this shift here.
这就是我们之前谈到的确保
This is what we were talking about earlier with make sure
当你做碰撞时 移动任何
when you do a collision, shift whatever is
走出你正在碰撞的任何东西的界限
moving outside the boundaries of whatever you're colliding with.
因此 self.ball.x得到的是brick.x减去8 因为球有8个像素宽
So self.ball.x gets brick.x minus eight because the ball is eight pixels wide.
为了获得更好的风格 它实际上应该是self.ball
It should actually be self.ball.width for a better style,
但这就是它本质上要转化为的
but that's essentially what it translates out to.
右边的边缘也是这样
Same thing for the right edge.
正六是因为它在右边
The plus six because it's on the right side.
所以如果我们在左边 它实际上和负2是一样的
So it's effectively the same thing as minus two if we're on the left side.
只是一种修复转角的方法 转角的奇怪问题
Just a sort of fixes corners, weird issues with corners.
但检查一下 基本上球是不是加上它的高度减2
But check in to see if basically the ball plus its height minus two
大于砖块加X加砖块宽度 这意味着
is greater than the brick plus X plus brick.width, which it means,
哦 我们撞到了屏幕的右边 砖头的右边
oh, we've collided with the right edge of the screen, of the brick.
然后如果Y小于砖块Y
And then if the Y is less than the brick.y,
然后我们撞上了砖头的顶部
then we've collided with the top of the brick,
否则 我们就撞到了底部
and otherwise, we've collided with the bottom.
对于顶部和底部 只要做我们对增量X所做的相同的事情
And with the top and the bottom, just do the same thing we did with delta X,
但对Delta Y进行此操作 但您仍在重新设置它
but do it with delta Y, but you're still resetting it.
因此 Ball.y得到brick.y减去8
So ball.y gets brick.y minus eight.
Ball.y得到brick.y加16 因为球拍或单独的砖
Ball.y gets brick.y plus 16 because the paddle or the individual bricks
有16个像素高
are 16 pixels tall.
这就是碰撞检测的要点
That's the gist of the collision detection.
然后如果我们真的--哦 还有一件事 我最终
And then if we actually-- oh, and one other thing that I ended up
把它放在这里只是为了让它更有趣一些
putting here just to make it a little bit more interesting,
这也与更复杂的碰撞检测有关
and this also ties into more complicated collision detection.
如果你的速度太快 很多时候它会跳过物体
If your velocity is too fast, a lot of the time it'll skip through objects,
这就给这些碰撞检测带来了很多问题
and then that causes a lot of problems with these collision detection
这些函数通常在数学上是非常正确的
functions that normally are very sort of mathematically correct
它们工作得很好
and they work well.
当它跳过什么时 它们就不能很好地工作
They don't work well when it skips over what
你实际上正试图与之相撞
you're trying to actually collide with.
这个问题的解决方案超出了本例的范围 但是
So a solution to that, which was beyond the scope of this example but something
我们在想 可能是在倒退到一定程度
we're thinking about, is perhaps stepping backwards a certain amount
时间 一定的像素量
of time, a certain amount of pixels.
也许可以从你的球所在的地方开始
Perhaps maybe start at where you where your ball was on one particular,
在最后一帧上 然后只需将其宽度和高度添加到其自身
on the last frame, and then just add its width and height to itself
直到它与某物相撞 直到它到达当前的增量X
until it collides with something, until it reaches whatever its current delta X
或者Y增量加上它的位置
or delta Y plus its position is.
这是一种方法
That's one way to do it.
就像是添加了一堆看不见的--
Sort of just adding a bunch of invisible--
无论你撞上的是什么 或者你用来碰撞的是什么--
whatever you're colliding with or whatever you're using to collide--
添加一堆看不见的那些来弥合差距 并检查其中任何一个
add a bunch of invisible those to bridge the gap and check into if any of those
对于碰撞 保持为True
hold true for a collision.
计算成本稍微高一点 但精确度要高得多
A little bit more computationally expensive, but a lot more accurate
从物理学的角度来说
in terms of the physics.
除此之外 一切都是一样的
And aside from that, everything is the same.
所以如果你看一下Breakout 4中的代码--
So if you look at the code in Breakout4--
从今以后 我要开得更快一点
and I'm going to go a little bit faster henceforth.
这可能是该计划中最丰盛的部分
That's probably the meatiest part of the program.
我们会遇到碰撞
We get collisions.
然后我会试着得到一个强有力的角度 这样我就可以演示--
And then I'll try and get a strong angle so I can demo the--
但这并不管用
that didn't work.
这实际上给出了一个较弱的角度
That actually gave a weaker angle.
所以如果你这样做 你靠近中心做 它会产生相反的效果
So if you do this and you do it close to the center, it has the opposite effect.
但这就是你要做的
But there you go.
这是一个更锐利的角度
That's a sharper angle.
所以现在你实际上可以更多地影响球
So now you can actually influence the ball in a little bit more
风度翩翩的方式
of a personable way.
你知道 它不仅仅是一个平坦的增量 Y变负--
You know, not just have it be a flat delta Y gets negative--
或者有效地得到负的增量Y
or get negative delta Y effectively.
那么对于这一切的主旨是如何运作的 有什么问题吗？
So any questions on sort of how the gist of all of that works?
好的
OK.
完美无缺
Perfect.
所以现在我们要进入更多一些有趣的东西
So now we're going to get into a little bit more of some fun stuff.
我们再做几个例子 然后休息一下
We'll do a couple more examples, then we'll take a break.
这就是心脏的最新情况
So this is the hearts update.
请注意屏幕的最上方 正如我在下面这些演示中所演示的
So notice that the very top of the screen, as I've demonstrated in these
幻灯片 我们只有几颗心
slides, we have just a few hearts.
其中一个是空的
One of them is empty.
我们早些时候展示了这个
We showed this earlier.
然后我们有一场屏幕上的比赛 这是我们的最终比分
And then we have a game over screen, which is our final score.
所以我要继续 我们只需要稍微看一下代码
So I'm going to go ahead and we're just going to look at the code a little bit
现在更快了 因为很多东西都相当简单
faster now since a lot of the stuff is fairly straightforward.
我要继续下去 打开--
I'm going to go ahead and open up the--
我首先要确保我在正确的文件夹中
I'm going to make sure I'm in the right folder first of all.
突破5.
Breakout5.
然后在--
And then in the--
所以我们要开始做的另一件事是--
so one other thing we're going to start doing is--
我刚才提到过这一点
I mentioned this earlier.
它将会是真实的
And it's going to be it's going to hold true
对于任何一种状态转换
for any of the sort of state transformations
这一切都发生在未来
that take place going forward.
我们没有保留全局变量 而是
Rather than keep global variables, we're going
在某种程度上消除资产表外的这种想法
to sort of do away with that idea outside of the asset tables
我们所拥有的只是因为这些是一种例外
that we have just because those are kind of an exception
并且可以合理地将它们放在一个称为资源的单独类中
and they could reasonably be put into a separate class called the resource
经理
manager.
我们将开始传入基本上就是我们当前的应用程序状态
We're going to start passing in what is basically our current app state,
或者至少是有意义的变量
or at least the variables that make sense.
这也是使用Reaction进行Web开发的常见范例
And this is a common paradigm in web development with React as well.
但基本上 我们需要的一切都是州与州之间的保存
But basically, everything that we need to be preserve state to state,
与其只保留全局变量
rather than just keeping global variables,
让我们在状态之间传递它们 因为状态机允许
let's pass them between the states because the state machine allows
我们需要在Change函数中执行此操作
us to do that in the change function.
然后不管它的Enter函数处于什么状态
And then whatever that state is in it's enter function,
它将可以访问它 并且它可以
it'll have access to that and it can just
将这些值设置为Self Dot Anywhere并使用它们
set those values to self dot whatever and use them.
但我们不再有全球变量
But we no longer have global variables.
我们只是想说 给你
We're just saying, here.
以下是对你继续下去很重要的价值观
Here's the values that are important for you to continue on.
然后 该状态将采用其值并进入下一状态
And then that state will take its values and go to the next state
然后说 哦 好的 这是你运作所需要的价值观
and say, oh, OK, here are the values that you need to function.
比如发球 打球 以及所有这些状态
Like the serve, play, and all those states
有核心游戏参与的人可能会
that have the core game play involved will probably
需要保持一个像桨一样的引用
need to maintain a reference to like the paddle,
更重要的是 我们所拥有的健康程度
and to the score, the amount of health we have.
但当我们走到最后 例如 然后我们不再真的
But when we get to the end, for example, and then we no longer really
需要一把桨 我们不再真的需要砖头或类似的东西
need a paddle, we no longer really need bricks or anything like that,
我们只需要知道我们的最高分是多少 这样我们就可以进入它
we just need to know what our high score is so that we can enter it
进入我们的高分名单 我们真正需要的
into our high score list, all we really need
要做的就是通过高分州进入或只通过我们的高分
to do is just pass in the high score state entry or just our high score,
就是这样
and that's it.
所以它封装了我们所有的数据
So it encapsulates all of our data.
一眼就能看出我们需要在两个州之间传递什么
And at a glance, we can sort of see what we need to pass between the states
以及哪些内容也将一目了然
and what's going to be relevant at a glance as well.
它只是清理了相当多的东西
It just clean things up quite a bit.
这就是我们现在在第35行所做的
So that's what we're doing now on line 35.
从今以后 我们将在我们所看到的每个州都这样做
And henceforth, we will do this in every state as we see,
但我打算在未来对它进行某种程度的掩盖
but I'm going to sort of glaze over it in the future.
我们现在有了一个ServeState
We have a ServeState now.
因此 作为一个ServeState 这与我们在Pong所做的非常相同
So a ServeState, this is very identical to what we did in Pong.
因此 我们只需等待用户按空格键
So we just wait for the user to press Space.
他们可以四处走动 然后当他们按下Enter键时
They can move around and then when they do press Enter,
基本上 球开始移动了
basically the ball starts moving.
然后我们使用以下命令更改此处的PlayState
And then we change the PlayState here using
所需的当前值
the current values that are necessary.
划桨、砖块、健康、得分和球
Paddle, bricks, health, score, and ball.
这些基本上是基本的变量
Those are basically the fundamental variables
我们需要它来跟踪我们的游戏状态
that we need in order to keep track of our GameState.
所以我们有一个ServeState 它将等待我们按Enter键
So we have a ServeState, it will wait for us to press Enter.
然后是我们的主路 我们有了一个新的心心桌
And then our main.lua, we have a new hearts table.
然后在208线上 因为我们要去
And then on line 208, because we're going
需要在几个州呈现健康和分数的能力
to need the ability to render health and render our score across several states,
比赛、发球、胜利、游戏结束--
Play, Serve, Victory, Game Over--
其实不是游戏结束 而是之前的三场比赛
actually not Game Over, but the three before that.
我们不想重复这些行为
We don't want to duplicate those behaviors,
所以我只调用了一个名为Render Health的函数 它
so I'm just calling a function called Render Health, which
只是吸收任何健康的东西 然后
just takes in whatever health is and then
我们只需将X设置为虚拟宽度减去100
we just set an X to virtual width minus 100.
然后 为了我们的健康 画一颗心
And then for however many health we have, draw a heart
从红心精灵纸上 我把心分开
from the hearts sprite sheet, which I separated the hearts out
分成更小的图像 这样你就可以把它们分成8乘8的
into a smaller image so you can just split them on like eight by eight
或者什么都行
or whatever it is.
但只要把它们画出来 然后把11加到X上
But just draw those and then add 11 to X,
继续前进 直到我们拔出我们有多少颗心
and just keep going until we've drawn out however many hearts we have.
这将吸引满满的心
That will draw full hearts.
然后 三减健康将会给我们带来多少我们错过的健康
And then three minus health will give us however many health we're missing.
所以如果我们取一个损伤点 这将等于1
So if we took a point of damage, this is going to be equal to one.
然后它会画出一颗空的心 否则它会画出两颗空的心
So then it'll draw one empty heart after that or it'll draw two empty hearts.
所以 画出我们有多少颗饱满的心 然后画出空虚的心
So draw however many full hearts we have, then draw the empty hearts.
这是我们从图像中得到的两个独立的精灵
And those are two separate sprites that we get from the image.
这将对我们的健康产生影响
And that will have the effect of drawing our health.
然后我们的分数很简单 它接受一个分数变量 我们在这里传递
And then our score is simply, it takes a score variable that we pass into here.
还请注意 渲染运行状况[INAUDIBLE]
And also note that the render health [INAUDIBLE]
和健康变量 并在这里传递给它
and health variable and pass into it here.
因此 在我们的PlayState中 我们在第135行调用这两个函数
And so in our PlayState, we are calling both of these functions on line 135.
好的 在第135行 我们正在计算我们是否
Well, on line 135, we are calculating whether we
走到屏幕边缘下方 这是游戏的另一个重要部分
go below the edge of the screen, which is another important part of the game.
显然 我们需要发现我们何时失去了健康
Obviously, we need to detect when we've lost health.
所以事情就是这么简单
So it's as simple as this.
如果它大于实际身高 健康就会减少1
If it's greater than the virtual height, decrement health by one.
如果它等于零 则更改为游戏结束
If it's equal to zero, change to Game Over.
否则 更改为ServeState
Else change to the ServeState.
请注意 我们将所有这些变量传入和传出我们的州
And note that we're passing in all these variables to and from our states.
那些重要的东西
The ones that are important.
比赛结束只需要得分 但发球需要任何东西
Game Over just needs score, but Serve needs whatever
我们已经在使用的变量
variables we were already using.
然后我们在这里调用Render Score和Render Health
And then down here we're calling render score and render health,
然后 GameOverState就是简单的--
and then the GameOverState is simply--
因为它接受参数列表中的分数
because it takes in score from the parameters list,
只需等待键盘输入返回到开始 然后渲染游戏结束
just wait for keyboard input to go back to the start and then render game over,
这是你的分数
here's your score.
这是自己的得分 然后就是这样
It's self.score, and then that's it.
非常简单
Very simple.
非常简单的状态
Very simple state.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：当然可以
COLTON OGDEN: Sure.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 这些州中有哪一个
COLTON OGDEN: The question was, do any of these states
有权访问他们的父文件吗？
have access to their parent file?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：一切正常吗？Lua全球运行吗？
COLTON OGDEN: Is everything in main.lua global functions?
是
Yes.
您声明的函数
Functions that you declare.
在main.lua中定义的基本上未指定为本地的任何内容
Anything that's basically not specified as local that you define in main.lua
将可在应用程序中的任何位置访问 包括函数
will be accessible anywhere in your application, including functions.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：你不必--问题是
COLTON OGDEN: You don't have to-- the question was,
你必须申报为公共物品吗？
do you have to declare as public?
不 没有公开的概念
No, there is no notion of public.
在LUA中 任何没有局部说明符的东西
In lua, anything that does not have a local specifier
被假定为全局的 即使它在嵌套作用域中
is assumed global, even if it's in a nested scope.
所以你可以有一个for循环 你可以有几个嵌套的for循环
So you could have a for loop, you could have several nested for loops
并声明一些不带局部变量的变量 该变量可以在任何地方访问
and declare some variable without local, that variable can be accessed anywhere
在它上面或外面
above it or outside of it.
所以使用局部变量非常重要
So it's pretty important to use local variables
当你没有显式地分配全局变量时
when you're not explicitly allocating something as global
只是为了避免for嵌套循环的错误
just to avoid the bug of for nested loops
你有一个变量名 比如hello 你可以在其他地方使用它
and you have some variable name like hello and you use it somewhere else.
好问题
Good questions though.
所以是的
So yeah.
我们现在有很多州
We have a bunch of states now.
我们有一个GameOverState 一个PlayState 我们
We have a GameOverState, a PlayState, we're
渲染我们的分数渲染我们的健康
rendering our score, rendering our health.
如果我们去看看Breakout 5--
If we go and take a look at Breakout5--
是另一扇窗吗？
is it a different window?
好了
There we go.
我们可以在顶部看到心脏
We can see hearts at the top.
零分
Score zero.
哦 我忘了说我们现在要加分了
Oh, and I forgot to mention the part where we actually add score now.
所以砖块本身在击中时 或者我应该说在PlayState中
So the bricks themselves in their on hit, or I should say in the PlayState,
在第81行 当我们检测到一个命中时 我们现在只是在分数上加10
on line 81 when we detect a hit, we're just adding 10 to the score for now.
但稍后我们会做一个计算
But later on, we'll do a calculation where
我们会考虑层次和颜色
we take tier and color into consideration
然后进行算术运算 得出每次击球的总得分
and then perform arithmetic on that to get our total score for each ball hit.
但是 是的 我们有我们的健康 我们有我们的分数
But yeah, we have our health, we have our score.
一旦我们受到足够的伤害
And then once we take enough damage, we'll
最终进入游戏结束屏幕
end up going to the Game Over screen.
游戏结束屏幕将返回到开始屏幕
The Game Over screen will go back to our Start screen.
所以有进步
So making progress.
然后可能是我最喜欢的更新
And then probably my favorite of the updates
在我们短暂休息之前是美丽的颜色更新
before we take a short break is the pretty colors update.
所以很明显我们可以
So what this does is clearly we can have--
我们已经更新了水平仪
we've updated our level maker.
所以我们不需要一堆静止的砖块
So rather than just having a bunch of very static bricks,
我们最终做了一个更复杂的过程生成
we end up doing a little bit more complicated procedural generation.
但这并不复杂
It's not complicated though.
在Breakout 6的levelmaker.lua中 我们有几个不同的常量
Just in levelmaker.lua in Breakout6, we have a few different constants here.
所以固体 交替 跳过 或没有
So solid, alternate, skip, or none.
实际上 我不认为我用了跳过或没有
Actually, I don't think I use skip or none.
基本上是固定的或者交替的
Just solid or alternate basically.
我们现在有旗子了
We have flags now.
列的数量
So number of columns.
我们确保它是奇数的 因为偶数列具有生成模式
And we ensure that it's odd because even columns with generating patterns
会导致不对称
leads to asymmetry.
因此 请确保列数为奇数
So make sure the number of columns is odd.
根据我们的级别生成最高级别和最高颜色
Generate the highest tier and the highest color based on our level.
所以在这种情况下 我们不会再往上走一层
So in this case, we'll go no higher of a tier
因为我们没有比三级更高的级别
than three because we have no higher tiers than three.
0 1 2 3
It goes zero, one, two, three.
然后 无论我们的水平除以5是多少
And then whatever our level divided by five is,
而且它只需要数学 地板
and it would just take math.floor.
Math.Floor基本上执行除法 然后截断
Math.floor takes in basically performing division and then truncating
小数点
the decimal point.
嗯 不是组织
Well, not division.
它只是从字面上截断了一个数字的小数点
It just literally truncates the decimal point off of a number.
所以这个水平除以5
So a level divided by five.
不管小数点前的数字是多少
Whatever that is before the decimal point.
级别模块五加三为最高颜色
Level modular five plus three for the highest color.
所以我们要骑车了
So we'll cycle.
我们会一遍又一遍地复习
We'll go over and over again.
走最高的颜色一 二 三 四 五 然后我们将进入一个新的层次
Go highest color one, two, three, four, five, and then we'll go to a new tier
级别除以5
with level divided by 5.
所以基本上 每五个级别就会在层中递增
So basically, every five levels will increment in tier,
然后我们再从蓝色开始
and then we'll start back at blue.
然后我们继续 继续 就像这样 每隔几行
And then we go on, and on, and on like that for every number of rows.
所以基本上我有几个--
So basically I have a few--
我将在这一点上稍加强调
I'm going to sort of glaze over this a little bit
就因为我们可能会赶不上时间
just because we're probably going to run short on time.
但我们基本上有两面旗帜
But we have basically two flags.
无论我们是跳过这一排的砖块 还是按颜色交替使用砖块
Whether we're skipping bricks in this row or alternating bricks color wise.
如果我们这样做 我们需要为它设置一个颜色和一个层
And if we do, we need to set a color for it and a tier.
然后我们基本上只是说 你知道的
And then we basically just say, you know,
与我们在生成随机行之前使用的逻辑相同
the same sort of logic that we had before we generated random rows
和列 但是如果我们打开了Alternate标志
and columns, but if we have the alternate flag on,
然后 正如我们在这里的一些照片中看到的 我们在这里有一个跳跃是真的
then as we can see in some of these photos here, here we have skip is true.
因此 该行的颜色设置为蓝色 但跳过为真
So the color for that row is set to the blue, but skip is true,
因此 每隔一块砖就会跳过循环的迭代
so every other brick is just going to skip that iteration of the loop.
这里也是一样 只是被1抵消了
Same thing here, only it's offset by one.
这里也是一样
Same thing here.
所以这是一种不错的小图案
So this is kind of a nice little pattern.
在每一种情况下--
And in each of these cases--
实际上 并不是每一个案例都是如此
actually not each of these cases.
请注意第三个参数 它还将Alternate设置为True
Notice this third one, it also set alternate to true.
所以它变成了绿色 紫色 绿色 紫色 绿色 紫色
So it goes green, purple, green, purple, green, purple.
所以逻辑是 如果Alternate为真 那么
And so the logic there is if alternate is true, then
只需在每次迭代中翻转颜色即可
just flip the color every iteration.
如果跳过为真 则不要每隔一次迭代生成一块积木 依此类推
If skip is true, don't generate a brick every other iteration, and so on
以此类推
and so forth.
如果有Solid 或者没有Alternate Equals True
And then if you have solid or if you don't have alternate equals true,
然后你就会有一块坚固的砖 就像这些蓝色的
then you have a solid brick like these blue ones.
如果你有替代但没有跳过 你就会得到这种模式
And if you have alternate but no skip, you get this sort of pattern
有绿色、紫色、绿色、紫色
where you have green, purple, green, purple.
你知道 任何随机的颜色
You know, any random color.
而且列数也是随机的
And then also the number of columns is random.
所以它可以--
So it can go--
这里有1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 但在最下面的这个上
here we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 but on this very bottom one,
看起来是负二 因为它只能这么宽
we have that minus two it looks like because it can only go that wide.
这里的那些也是如此
And in those here too.
尺寸要小一些
Smaller size.
那个没有空格
That one there's no spacing.
所以这些都是非常简单的概念
So these are very simple concepts.
比如 我们应该在这次迭代中跳过一个块吗？
Like should we skip a block this iteration?
我们应该换一下颜色吗？
Should we alternate the colors?
当你把它们放在一起时 就会产生
And when you put them all together, it produces
看起来像是几乎是手工制作的东西
things that look as if they were almost handcrafted.
就像这可能是某人做的一样
Like this could be made by somebody.
就像 这看起来像是有人做的
Like, that looks like it was made by somebody.
几乎每一次迭代
Pretty much every iteration of this.
我的意思是 即使是这样 那看起来也几乎是一个形状
I mean, even that, that looks like a shape almost.
这很简单 但在我看来 结果非常棒
Its just very simple but the results are pretty awesome in my opinion.
这就是我们正在做的事情背后的主旨
And so that's just the gist behind what we're doing.
我们只是在设置旗帜 然后说 你知道的
We're just setting flags and just saying, you know,
如果我们跳过这一轮 跳过每一次迭代
if we're skipping this turn and just every iteration,
每次我们铺开一块砖 在这一排上生出一块新砖
every time we lay out a brick and we spawn a new brick on this row,
要么做要么不做
just do or don't.
只要把它弄成彩色的就行了
Just make it's color--
如果我们是交替的 选择两种颜色 然后设置
pick two colors if we're alternating and then set
它的颜色是我们交替的任何关闭的颜色
its color to whatever the off color is that we're alternating.
如果我们跳过和交替 那么
And if we're skipping and alternating, then
我们只是在我们实际铺设的砖头上做
we're just doing whenever we're on a brick that we're actually laying
就是当我们改变颜色时 交替的颜色
is when we change the color, the alternate color.
就像我说的 我不会讲太多细节
And so like I said, I won't go into too much detail.
我很乐意在课后讨论发电机
Happy to talk about the generator after class.
但我们时间不多了
But just because we're running short on time,
我会在上面挥舞双手
sort of going to wave my hands over it.
但简单来说就是这样
But that's it in a nutshell.
在我们休息五分钟之前还有问题吗？
So any questions before we take a break for five minutes?
- 是吗-是的
Yes?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 在这种编程的情况下
COLTON OGDEN: The question is, in an instance with this programming
如果球的速度快到我们实际上在砖块里面
if the ball were so fast that it we're actually inside the brick,
会怎样？
would it what?
记者：还会反弹吗？
AUDIENCE: Would it still bounce back?
科尔顿·奥格登：它还会反弹吗？
COLTON OGDEN: Would it still bounce back?
答案是不 不会
The answer is no, it wouldn't.
此实现不考虑速度
This implementation doesn't take into consideration velocity
太快了
that goes too fast.
主要有两个原因
Mainly to-- for two reasons.
第一 它的实现是不平凡的 第二
One, it's non-trivial to implement, and two,
这是一件有趣的事情
it's an interesting thing to look at, and observe,
并且在你实现自己的游戏时要有意识
and be conscious of as you go forward in implementing your own games.
当前的代码 如果它被夹在砖块里
The current code, if it gets clipped inside of the brick,
它的边缘不会突出到砖的外面
it will have no edges that are peaking outside of the brick
因此 它将默认为最终条件
and therefore, it will default to the final condition, which
是最后一个else子句 它把它放在砖块下面
is the last else clause, which puts it below the brick.
所以它只会在砖下面
So it'll just go below the brick.
就像是从下面弹出来的
It'll almost be as if it came in from the underside and bounced out.
但是就像我之前提到的 如果你想实现一些东西
But like I alluded to earlier, if you want to implement something
像这样 你需要把X帧和X +1帧分割开来
like this yourself, you would have to slice up frame X and frame X plus one
如果三角洲很宽
into the size of the ball if the delta is so wide
它要么在砖里面要么在砖外面
that it either goes inside of a brick or it goes outside of a brick,
还是漏了一块砖
or if it skips a brick.
这个解决了这个问题
And this sort of solves that problem.
它解决了这两个问题 但它有点多
It solves both of those problems, but it's a little more
比我们在这个例子中所能涵盖的要多
than we can cover in this example.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
好吧
All right.
休息五分钟继续工作
Let's take five and get back to it.
好吧
All right.
我们回来了
And we're back.
下一步就是我们有一个动态的布局
So the next step is we have basically a layout dynamically
现在产生了许多有趣的砖 但我们还没有真正
generated of interesting bricks now, but we haven't really
实施了对其中任何一项的评分
implemented scoring any of these.
我们只有分数加10 这就是
We just have score gets score plus 10, which
其实并不是特别有趣
isn't really particularly interesting.
因此 Breakout 7就是我所说的层更新 即
So Breakout7 is what I call the tier update, which
应该允许我们命中比基本蓝色更高级别的块
should allow us to hit blocks that are a higher tier than just base blue.
如果它们的颜色高于基蓝 它们应该降到更低的颜色
And if they are of a higher color than base blue, they should go down a color.
因此 如果我们回头看 这个等级是蓝色的
So the hierarchy was, if we look back, blue
变成绿色 变成红色 变成紫色 变成金色
goes to green goes to red goes to purple goes to gold.
如果某个东西是更高的层次 它就会
And if something is a higher tier, it goes
到它下面的下一个颜色 但在同一层
to the next color below it but at that same tier,
除非它恰好是蓝色和灰色的 在这种情况下
unless it happens to be like blue and gray, in which case
它会变回蓝色
it'll go back to blue.
那么 我们如何在这个系统的基础上实施评分呢？
So how might we implement scoring based on this system?
我们需要什么？
What do we need?
我们需要些什么呢？
What pieces do we need?
我们已经拥有了哪些我们可以用来实现这一点的东西？
What pieces do we already have that we can use to make this happen?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：什么？
COLTON OGDEN: I'm sorry?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：所以答案是砖块指数
COLTON OGDEN: So the answer was the brick index.
所以 是的 砖皮和颜色就是碎片
So yes, the brick skin and color are the pieces.
是
Yes.
所以这些都是砖块砌成的田地
So those are fields of brick.
所以如果我们敞开心扉
So if we open up--
我要去看《越狱7》
I'm going to go up to Breakout7.
我可能会开始推迟很多代码
And I'm going to start probably deferring a lot of this code
敬未来的阅读
to future reading.
但这里的砖块 层数和颜色--
But in brick here, the tier and the color--
对不起 不是皮 但皮是用来划桨的
sorry, not skin, but skin is for the paddle.
但这块砖有一层 它有一种颜色
But the brick has a tier and it has a color.
所以我们需要在这里进行一些算术运算
And so we need to perform some arithmetic on that here.
这基本上就是第44行到第58行的意思
And that's essentially what lines 44 through 58 is.
所以基本上--哦 我道歉
So basically-- oh, I apologize.
这实际上并不是算术上的问题
That's not actually where the arithmetic is.
44 这是可以计算的 但这是一小段代码
44, that does compute, but this is the bit of code
这就计算了如果我们发生碰撞 我们实际上可以如何倒退
that computes how we can actually go backwards if we make a collision.
所以如果我们撞上了一块砖 它的层级比一层高
So if we collide with a brick and it's of a higher tier than one
而且它是一种比蓝色更高的颜色 它应该被带回一个台阶
and it's a higher color than blue, it should be brought back one step.
但如果它恰好是蓝色的 在这种情况下 self.COLOR会得到一个
But if it happens to be blue, in which case self.color gets one
因为蓝色是其中之一 那么就应该把它从比赛中剔除
because blue is one, then it should just be removed from play
就像我们以前做的那样
just like we've done before.
只是现在 我们也在考虑层次感和色彩
Only now, we're also taking in tier and color.
因此 我们根据我们所处的索引递减层
So we're decrementing tier based on what index we're at
而且我们的颜色也在减少
and we're decrementing color.
然后这实际上会在我们的PlayState中使用
And then this actually gets used in our PlayState.
如果我们转到第81行 它之前刚刚
If we go to line 81, which previously just
让自己得分 得分加一 这里有一点数学知识
had self.score gets self.score plus one, there's a little bit of math here.
不过 这很简单
It's very simple though.
就是砖头 200倍
Just brick.tier times 200.
因此 让这些层的价值达到100
So make the tiers worth 100.
再加上砖块 颜色乘以25
Plus brick.color times 25.
因此 如果层为零 如果它是基数 那么我们将
And so if tier is zero, if it's a base then we're
只是拿不到那200英镑的奖金
just not going to get that 200 bonus.
但在第一层 一切都将是值得的
But the first tier, everything is going to be worth
25倍 不管它是什么颜色
25 times whatever its color is.
一、二、三、四、五
So one, two, three, four, five.
然后再加上200加上砖块的颜色
And then add 200 plus the brick.color for when
我们到了下一组砖
we get to the next set of bricks.
这样做的结果是--
And so the result of this is--
我相信这是《图形用户界面突破7》
I believe this is GUI Breakout7.
如果我们撞到了一块砖--
And then if we hit a brick--
既然这个是蓝色的 它应该会消失
since this one is blue, it should disappear.
我们也在播放一种新的声音
And we're playing a new sound as well.
新的 就像 死亡的声音只是为了清楚
New, like, death sound just to make it clear.
但请注意 它们会改变颜色
But notice they change colors.
这就是我们要做的一切
So that's all we're doing.
我们只是想要他们的等级或颜色
We're just taking their tier or their color
只需对其执行一个简单的减量
and just performing a simple decrement on it.
往回循环
Looping back.
在我们下一层的情况下 我们应该循环返回
In the event that we go down a tier, we should loop back up
到较低层的最高颜色
to the highest color of the lower tier.
所以我会让你们看看这方面的代码
So I'll let you look at the code for that
如果你想对它有一个更低层次的理解
if you want to sort of get a more low level understanding of it,
但这是一种高层次的理解
but that's the sort of high level understanding.
我想向你们介绍的下一个重要概念是
The next big concept that I'd like to introduce you guys to
是一个粒子系统
is a particle system.
因此 粒子系统在视频游戏中相当普遍
And so particle systems are fairly omnipresent in video games,
我会说 因为它们产生的效果
I would say, because they make effects that
或者很难用简单的精灵来做
or otherwise difficult to do with simple sprite
编辑可以非常容易和现实地实现
editing achievable very easily and realistically.
例如 就像火一样
Just like fire, for example.
非常有机的 流畅的 有很多东西在进行
Things that are very organic, and flowy, and have a lot going on
通常用粒子系统表示得更好
are often better represented with particle systems
而不是使用简单的精灵动画
than they are with simple sprite animation.
有谁知道我们如何才能--
So does anybody know how we might be able to--
粒子系统如何在引擎盖下工作？
how a particle system might work underneath the hood?
我想我以前提到过这一点
I think I alluded to it previously.
是
Yes.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
所以他说的是为了生火
So what he said was in order to make fire,
例如 只需产生一束粒子
for example, just spawn a bunch of particles
靠近你的火种产生的中心 然后在它的外面
close to the center of wherever your fire is spawning and then outside of it
产卵较少
spawn fewer.
这绝对是一种让火发挥作用的方法
That is absolutely a way to get fire to work,
同时也要考虑到粒子的移动
and also taking into consideration the travel of your particles.
例如 你可能会非常密集地产生一吨的火粒子
For example, you might spawn a ton of fire particles really densely,
但或许他们有某种逻辑让他们往上走
but then maybe they have some logic that makes them go upwards.
也许它们有一个负的增量Y 然后是某种加速度
Maybe they have a negative delta Y and then some sort of acceleration
因此 他们已经有了一些踪迹
so they've sort of trail off.
然后也许是如何获得更逼真的火
And then maybe sort of how to get a more realistic fire
看 它们向上移动 然后逐渐消失
look, they travel sort of upwards and then fade away.
所以火的运作方式 某种程度上是在思考事物
So the way fire works, sort of thinking of things
就这样的粒子而言 你可以达到很多效果
in terms of particles like that, you can achieve a lot of effects.
例如 我们如何实现吸烟？
How might we implement, like, smoke, for example?
同样的系统
Same system.
所以我们可以在粒子效果中使用计时器
So we could have maybe a timer in our particle effect,
甚至是一种转变 因为在粒子系统中
or even a transition because in particle systems,
通常 您可以在粒子之间过渡颜色
often you have the ability to transition colors between particles.
比方说 你从红色开始 到黄色
Let's say you start off red, go to yellow,
然后 您的粒子系统可能会过渡到灰色或棕色
and then maybe your particle system transitions to gray or brown.
然后随着时间的推移 你的颗粒物会上升 它们会消散
And then over time, your particles are going up, they're dissipating.
它们也变暗了 它们变成了棕色
And they're also turning dark, they're turning brown,
它给你一种火的错觉
it sort of gives you the illusion of fire.
我们不会做任何事情 因为
And we won't be doing anything necessarily as
在我们的代码中如此复杂 但在Breakout 8中 我们
complex as this in our code here, but in Breakout8, we
将使用Love的一种集成粒子系统 它只是
will be using Love's sort of integrated particle system which is just
Love.graph ics.newarticlessystem
love.graphics.newparticlesystem.
它接受纹理 因为所有粒子系统都需要某种
And it takes in a texture because all particle systems need some sort
质地作为它们的基础
of texture as their foundation.
然后它需要它最大限度地释放出的粒子的数量
And then it needs the number of particles that it could maximally emit.
因此每个单独的粒子系统都可以向上发射
And so each individual particle system can emit up
到粒子的某个实例
to a certain instance of particles.
在数量、速度和诸如此类的东西上
And in the number, and speed, and whatnot of all
这些颗粒最终是决定因素
those particles is ultimately the determining factor
你如何才能得到一个幻觉
for how you can get an illusion.
回到上周的演讲 幻觉 就像 这不是火 不是烟
Back to last week's lecture, illusions, like, it's not fire, it's not smoke,
它只是一群粒子在响应
it's just a bunch of particles responding
用颜色和加速度之类的东西
with colors and acceleration and stuff.
但在Love2D中 粒子系统为您提供了很多功能
But there's a lot of functions that particle system gives you in Love2D,
所以我鼓励你们看看这个链接 只是为了探索其中的一些
so I encourage you to look at that link just to explore some of them.
Love2d.org/wiki/articlessystem
Love2d.org/wiki/particlesystem.
我们将使用其中的几个
We'll be using a few of them.
在这里 我将简要地向你们展示
Here I'm going to just briefly show you.
所以当每一块砖被击中时
So each individual brick when it gets hit
需要一个自己的粒子系统
is going to need a particle system of its own.
因为我们的目标是--
Because our goal is--
我将为您运行代码 这样您就可以看到它
I'll run the code for you so you can see it.
因此 如果你转到Breakout 8 然后你运行它
So if you go to Breakout8 and then you run it,
我们有一点粒子 你们在最后看到的
we have a little bit of particles you saw there at the very end.
你可能看得更清楚一点的蓝色
The blue you were probably able to see a little bit better.
然后是最后一次
And then one last time.
所以它会产生一堆微小的粒子
So it spawns a bunch of little particles.
所以有没有人能告诉我他们认为这些粒子
So can anyone tell me how they think the particles are
一言以蔽之？
behaving sort of in a nutshell?
粒子的逻辑是什么？
What the logic is for the particles?
观众：[听不见]稍微有点随意
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] slightly random.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
有点随机
Slightly random.
如果你看它 你也会注意到它们往往是向下的
And if you look at it, you'll also notice that they tend to go downwards.
所以知道了这一点 我们大概可以假设
So knowing that, we can probably just assume
它们有一个趋向于正Y的加速度
that they have an acceleration that tends towards positive Y.
这基本上就是我们真正需要做的事情
And that's essentially all we really need to do.
我们向外产生一束粒子 然后把它们放在一起--
We spawn a bunch of particles outwards and then just set them--
他们都有一辈子的时间
they have all a lifetime.
它们会持续一段时间
They last for a certain amount of time.
然后它们会在两种颜色之间褪色
And then they fade between two colors.
在这种情况下 我们从红色褪色为透明或其他任何颜色
In this case, we fade from red to transparent or whatever color it is.
然后在生命周期过去之后 它会产生整体的影响
And then after the lifetimes elapsed, it has the overall effect
这种闪烁的、基于重力的效果
of sort of this glimmering, gravity based effect,
但它实际上只是一堆粒子
but it's really just a bunch of particles that are
设置为在不同方向产卵
set to spawn in different directions.
为此道歉
Apologize for that.
所以我们来看看
So we'll take a look.
它将出现在我们的《突破8》的砖块课上
It's going to be in our brick class here in Breakout8.
所以我们要去布里克
So we're going to go to brick.
我们在这里储存了一堆颜色
We have a bunch of colors that we're storing here.
所以如果你注意到了 粒子系统采用的是任何砖块的颜色
So if you notice, the particle systems adopt the color of whatever brick
他们的打击只是为了让它保持一致
they're hitting just so that it stays sort of congruent
与我们正在看的东西相吻合
with what we're looking at.
所以我们只是在这里存储了一堆颜色
So we're just storing a bunch of colors here.
我也不会太担心这一点
And I wouldn't worry too much about this.
这些只是精灵调色板中的颜色
These are just colors from the sprite palette
我们用在我们的精灵艺术上
that we used with our sprite art.
有一些特定的颜色只在那个精灵中使用
There's specific colors that are only used in that sprite.
一般来说 有一个调色板
And having a palette, generally speaking,
让你的作品看起来更有凝聚力
allows your art to look a little bit more cohesive
当你在做精灵艺术 而不是任性地挑选颜色
when you're doing sprite art as opposed to just picking colors willy nilly.
如果你说 哦 这个调色板我只会用16或32种颜色
If you say, oh, I'm going to only use 16 or 32 colors for this palette,
你会看起来更有凝聚力 而且
you'll sort of have a more cohesive look and also
非常复古的外观 因为硬件通常是
a very retro look because often hardware was
对于较旧的系统 仅限于一定数量的颜色
limited to a certain amount of colors back in the day for older systems.
所以我很高兴--
So it's nice to--
顺便说一句 我们下周也会讨论这个问题
as an aside-- and we'll look at it next week as well.
当你在做自己的精灵艺术时 试着使用更少的颜色
Looking at when you're doing your own sprite art, try to use fewer colors
然后这会给你--它也会让你更容易
and then that will give you-- it also makes it easier for you.
你不必花时间来挑选 我想要这种绿色
You don't have to spend time choosing I want to have this shade of green.
我想知道它看起来好不好
I wonder if it looks good.
如果你只有两种深浅绿色或半深浅绿色可供选择
If you only have two shades of green or semi shades of green to choose from,
这就是你能做的一切
that's all you've got.
你必须尽你所能凑合着使用它
You have to make do with it what you can.
所以我们在这里做的是从调色板中存储五种颜色
So what we're doing here is we're storing five colors from our palette.
我们将利用这一点
We're going to use this.
然后当我们启动我们的.
And then when we trigger our--
就在这里 我们正在初始化一个粒子系统
so right here we're initializing a particle system.
因此 psystem得到了love.graph ics.newarticlessystem
So psystem gets love.graphics.newparticlesystem.
然后是几个函数
And then these are a few functions.
因此 您可以在维基中查看这些功能的实际运行方式
So feel free to look in the wiki for how these functions actually behave.
但终生加速和面积扩散
But lifetime acceleration and area spread
只是在某种程度上影响了
just are sort of the properties that influence
我们的粒子系统的行为方式
the way our particle systems behave.
所以使用我们当前的颜色
And so using whatever our current color is,
我们将使用setColors函数设置psystem的颜色
we're going to set our psystem's colors using setcolors function.
我们要把它设置在两种颜色之间
We're going to set it between two colors.
层Alpha的颜色为55倍 Alpha为零的颜色
Color with 55 times tier alpha and color with zero alpha.
因此 层数越高 粒子越亮
So the higher the tier, the brighter the particles,
但如果这有道理的话 它们总是会逐渐消失到零阿尔法
but they'll always fade to zero alpha, if that makes sense.
然后我们就会排放64
And then we'll just emit 64.
这些都在HIT功能中
And this is all in the hit function.
所以我们基本上所做的就是在我们的命中中添加这个粒子系统触发器
So all we've basically done is just add this particle system trigger in our hit
函数 它具有我们前面看到的行为的结果
function, and it has the result of the behavior that we saw earlier.
那么 关于粒子系统或我们如何使用它们有什么问题吗？
So any questions on particle systems or how we use them?
因此 级别9是进度更新
So level 9 is the progression update.
因此 此更新的目的是让我们从第一个级别开始
So the purpose of this update is to allow us to go from level one
从两个到三个到四个 开始变得更有趣
to two to three to four and start get more interesting level
一代人都是这样的
generation that way.
这件事的主旨在于我们--
The gist of this is in our--
所以如果你看看我们的StartState--
so if you look at our StartState--
所以我们真正需要做的就是存储一个级别 只需存储一个数字
so all we need to really do to store a level is just to store a number.
然后我们在哪里递增这个数字？
And then where do we increment the number?
或者我们什么时候增加我应该说的数字？
Or when do we increment the number I should say?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：没错
COLTON OGDEN: Exactly.
因此 我们增加了级别
So we increment the level.
我们进入下一阶段 当所有的砖块
We go to the next level when all of the bricks
正在进行中已到达那里 正在进行中标志设置为假
are in play have gotten there in play flag set to false.
所以我们没有有效发挥作用的刺头
So we have no pricks that are in play effectively.
所以在我们的StartState中--
So in our StartState--
让我们继续看《突破9》
so let's go ahead and look at Breakout9.
所以 StartState
So StartState.
我们正在通过这里的一层
We're passing in level gets one here.
我们只是要开始了
We're just going to start off.
当我们要去StartState的时候 我们只需要通过等于1的级别
When we're going to StartState, we're just going to pass level equals one.
从今以后 任何时候我们从打球到发球的任何状态变化
And then henceforth, anytime we do any state changes from play to serve
而胜利 正如我们将看到的 胜利是我们的新的
and to victory, as we'll see, victory being our new,
哦 你清除了这个级别
oh, you cleared this level.
这是下一个关口
Here's the next level.
我们只是要超过他们之间的水平
We're just going to pass the level between them.
然后在PlayState中 这里的重要代码在204行
And then in PlayState, the important bit of code here is on line 204.
所以这只是一个名为check Vicary的函数
So this is just a function called checkVictory,
正如詹姆斯所说的那样
which is exactly as James said.
我们将遍历整个表 并只说它是否在运行
We're going to iterate over the entire table and just say if it's in play,
返回错误 因为我们没有取得胜利
return false because we're not in victory
如果我们有任何砖块在发挥作用
if we have any bricks that are in play.
但如果我们不满足该条件 则返回TRUE
But return true if we didn't meet that condition.
所以这只是一种简单的方式 让我们检查
And so this is just a simple way for us to check whether or not
我们取得了胜利
we are in a victory.
因此 在我们的PlayState中同一文件的第88行
And so on line 88 of the same file in our PlayState,
我们只是想说 嘿 如果我们做了任何砖头之后 自己检查胜利
we're just checking to say, hey, if self.checkVictory after we do any brick
命中--
hit--
因为在那个时候 我们刚刚设置的一块砖是错误的--
because that's when we've just set a brick to in play is false--
只要检查胜利就好
just check victory.
如果是这样的话 播放一个新的声音 就像一个快乐的声音
And if so, play a new sound like a happy sound
我们已经取得了胜利 然后就把一切都抛诸脑后了
that we've done a victory, and then just pass everything
进入我们这里拥有的新的维克托州
into the new VictoryState that we have here.
而VictoryState仅仅是一种消息状态
And the VictoryState is simply a sort of just a message state.
所以它所做的只是像以前一样渲染一切
So all it does is just renders everything as before,
但它只是说你目前的水平已经完成了
but it just says your current level complete.
自我.级别完成
Self.level complete.
然后按Enter键服务 它将返回到ServeState
And then press Enter to serve and it'll go back to the ServeState
一旦发生这种情况
as soon as that happens.
然后 这就是实际进展发生的地方
And then here is where the actual progression happens.
当我们转到ServeState时 我们有自己的级别 但我们想要添加一个
When we go to the ServeState, we have our level but we want to add one to it.
因此 当我们触发到下一个状态的转换时 我们需要做的就是
So all we need to do when we trigger a transition into our next state, just
在这里将级别递增1 并创建
increment level by one here, and also create
一个新的地图 因为砖块需要重新开始 因为我们有一个新的关卡
a new map because bricks needs to get restarted because we have a new level.
自我 级别加一
Self.level plus one.
这将会产生 哦 我们已经从第一级到第二级的效果
And that'll have the effect of, oh, we've gone from level one to two
当我们在PlayState和VictoryState之间穿梭时 会有三到四个人等等
to three to four et cetera when we go between PlayState to the VictoryState
回到ServeState
back to the ServeState.
那么 对这一切是如何运作的有什么问题吗？
So any questions on how any of this works?
是
Yes.
观众：你需要担心垃圾回收吗？
AUDIENCE: Do you have to worry about garbage collection for any
所有的砖块吗？
of the bricks at all?
或者这是由爱情引擎以某种方式处理的？
Or is that handled by the Love engine somehow?
科尔顿·奥格登：垃圾收集是由Love处理的
COLTON OGDEN: Garbage collection is handled by Love.
是
Yes.
嗯
Yeah.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yes.
因为问题是 你需要担心垃圾收集吗？
Because the question was, do you have to worry about garbage collection
当我们清理砖块并添加新砖的时候？
when we are sort of clearing away the bricks and adding new bricks?
砖桌 这张桌子 它是
The self.bricks table, this table here, it's
被分配到一张全新的桌子上 这张桌子来自velmap.createmap
getting assigned to a brand new table from levelmap.createmap.
当不存在对现有表的引用时
When there are no references to an existing table,
Lua的垃圾收集器将在任何地方触发
lua's garbage collector will trigger at whatever
它被设置为动态触发和清除所有这些
interval it's set to trigger and clear up all that for you dynamically.
就像Java的工作方式一样
Just like the same way that Java works.
几乎一模一样
Almost identical.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
好的
All right.
所以我们有进步
So we have progression.
为了速度 我不做演示
In the sake of speed, I won't demo.
这也需要一段时间 因为我们必须清除整个关卡
It also takes a while just because we have to clear an entire level then
更上一层楼
get to the next level.
但这就是这种行为的运作方式
But that's how the behavior works.
这种情况的下一种迭代是高分
The next sort of iteration of this is high scores.
我将进行测试 以确保这是否真的有效
And I will test to make sure whether or not this is actually working.
我知道我改变了一些东西
I know I changed some stuff.
嗯
Yeah.
这么高的分数
So high score.
让我们调试一下
Let's debug for a second.
因此 在Breakout 10中 HighScoreState第38行
So HighScoreState line 38 in Breakout10.
所以 HighScoreState
So HighScoreState.
然后问题是[INAUDIBLE]索引领域的高分
And then the issue was [INAUDIBLE] to index field high scores.
零值
A nil value.
好的
OK.
所以这意味着--
So that means that--
好的
OK.
我想我可能知道问题所在 但这是因为我
I think I might know the issue, but it's because I
已转换为新用户 该新用户在此上没有活动的已保存文件
transitioned to a new user that doesn't have a saved file active on this.
因此 将过渡到love.file系统的方式 它
The way that will transition, therefore, into love.file system, which
它引入的主要新事物是《突破10》的S--所以写文件
is Breakout10's main new thing that it introduces-- so writing files
到您的文件系统的操作使用love.filessystem完成[INAUDIBLE]
to your file system is done [INAUDIBLE] with love.filesystem.
有几件事
And there's a few things.
所以Love会自动给你一个目录 一个保存的目录
So Love automatically gives you a directory, a save directory
这几乎是硬编码
that's pretty much hard coded.
关于如何不使用该目录 有几个例外
There are a few exceptions as to how to not use that directory,
但它假定您一直在使用该目录
but it assumes that you're always using that directory.
除了极少数例外 您将始终使用该文件夹
And with very few exceptions will you always use that folder.
它就像Windows上的本地应用程序数据 以及应用程序支持
It's like app data local on Windows, and application support,
以及您在Mac上的应用程序的名称
and the name of your application on Mac.
但它是Love拥有读写权限的子文件夹
But it's a subfolder that Love has read and write access to
用于您的文件系统上的文件
for files on your file system.
您可以检查它是否与love.filesystem.存在于某个路径中
You can check whether it exists with love.filesystem.exists at some path.
您可以使用一些数据写入该路径 这些数据是字符串值
You can write to that path with some data, that data being a string value.
然后love.filesystem.line是一个迭代器
And then love.filesystem.lines is an iterator,
这将允许您查看任何数据
which will allow you to look over any of the data that's
在给定位置的文件中
in a file at a given location.
是
Yes.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
观众：如果你[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Does this work if you [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：应该是这样
COLTON OGDEN: It should.
实际上 我们现在可以把它拉出来看看
We can pull that up now actually and see.
因为我知道他们的2D爱情--
Because I know on their Love2D--
因此 文件系统
so file system.
所以问题是他把他的.
So the question was he ported his--
当你将Love应用程序移植到iPhone上时
when you port your Love app to the iPhone,
它会有同样的行为吗 如果你是--
will it have the same sort of behavior if you're--
在iPhone上 它会有同样的保存目录行为吗？
on an iPhone, will it have the same sort of save directory behavior?
而且看起来它还没有正式出现在这里
And it looks like it's not officially on here.
我知道有一个用于Love2D的iOS端口
I know that there is an iOS port for Love2D,
或者将其发送到Love2D的能力
or the ability to send it to Love2D.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：我想是的
COLTON OGDEN: I have to imagine yes.
它可能有某种--
It probably has some sort of--
我并不完全熟悉iOS是如何处理本地存储的
I'm not entirely familiar with how iOS handles sort of local storage,
但我假设只是从桌面抽象出来的方式
but I'm assuming that just in the way that it's been abstracted for desktops
而对于Android 它也是为iOS抽象的
and for Android, it's also abstracted for iOS.
我自己还没有测试过
Haven't tested it myself.
我会用这段代码做实验 看看有没有可能
I would experiment and see actually maybe with this code.
看看你能不能让它在持续的高分下发挥作用
See if you can maybe get it working with persistent high scores.
我知道iOS通常允许您在每个应用程序中存储少量数据
I know that iOS does typically let you store a small amount of data per app
在某个地方 一个固定的地方 但我不是
in some location, a fixed location, but I'm not
完全确定这是即兴的事情
entirely sure what that is offhand.
我可以更深入地研究一下 然后想出一个--
I can look into it more and come up with a--
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
我的意思是 不是来自第一手 因为我没有机器人
I mean, not from firsthand because I don't have an Android,
但它有官方的Android支持
but it has official Android support.
所以我猜是的 但我还没测试过
So I'm guessing it does, but I haven't tested it.
我还没有在Android上手动测试它来验证这一点
I have not tested it manually on Android to verify that.
不过 是的
But yes.
我相信--因为在之前的目录中 当它
I believe-- because in the prior directory we were looking at when it
展示了--
showed--
哦 实际上就在这上面
oh, it's actually up here.
这条路在这里
This path here.
这个数据/user/0/love2d.android
This data/user/0/love2d.android.
文件保存
file save.
在我看来 这是一条官方的道路
That looks to me like it's the official sort of path
这些数据存储在Android设备上 供应用程序使用
that data is stored on an Android device for application.
所以我还没有亲自测试过
So I haven't tested it myself.
但如果你有一个机器人 你很好奇 或者可能是一个仿真器
But if you have an Android and you're curious or maybe an emulator,
试一试 看看它是否奏效
give it a shot and see if it works.
哦 这里甚至写着 有各种各样的保存地点
Oh, and it even says here, there are various save locations.
如果它们不起作用 你可以看到实际位置
And if they don't work, you can see what the actual location
就是这里的这个功能
is with this function here.
Love.filesystem.get保存目录
The love.filesystem.get save directory.
这可能也适用于iOS 所以我很想知道
That may work on iOS as well, so I'd be curious to hear about
这是否真的能解决这个问题
whether that actually works on that.
嗯
Yeah.
这就是要点所在
So that's the gist.
通过使用love.filessystem抽象 我们可以读写文件
Using the love.filesystem abstraction lets us read and write files.
然后我们可以直接粘贴 也可以直接保存任何数据
We can then just paste or we can just save whatever data
我们想要那个目录中的任何地方
we want anywhere within that directory.
我们可以在那里创建文件 然后使用这些文件来存储我们的
We can just create files in there and then use those to store our,
你知道 游戏世界 或者角色简介 或者诸如此类的东西
you know, sort of game worlds, or character profiles, or whatnot.
我们将如何实施一份类似高分名单的计划？
How would we maybe go about implementing sort of like a high score list?
所以我会找的
So I'll look.
这里有一张照片
There's a picture here.
所以我们有10分
So we have 10 scores.
我们就假设这个问题已经解决了
We'll assume that's fixed.
每个分数都有一个名称 然后每个分数都有一个实际分数
Each of the scores has a name, and then each of the scores has an actual score.
所以我们真正需要做的就是最终存储这些名字
So all we really need to do is just store ultimately the names
然后是比分
and then the scores.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：所以我们将使用一个数组
COLTON OGDEN: So we'll use an array.
他们的回答是 我们将使用按该分数排序的数组
Their response was we'll use an array as sorted by that score.
嗯
Yeah.
从本质上说 就是这样
Essentially that's exactly it.
我们只需要保留一个计分表 每个表
We're just going to keep a score table and each table
将会有一张小桌子
is going to have a sub table.
这些条目中的每一个 从一到十
And each of those entries, one through ten,
将会有一个名字和一个分数
is going to have a name and a score.
然后 一旦我们完成了应用程序
And then once we're done with our application,
我们将只使用love.filesystem.write
we'll just use love.filesystem.write.
我们必须将所有这些内容转换为一个字符串
We'll have to convert all of those into a string
因为我们不能只拿一张桌子 然后把它吐到一个文件里
because we can't just take a table and then spit that out into a file.
我们必须把它变成某种我们可以拯救的形式
We have to actually make it into some form that we can save
然后以某种方式重新装填
and then reload back in somehow.
你认为什么是最有效的方式 或者我们可以做到这一点的一种方式？
What would be the most efficient way, do you think, or a way we can do this?
可能只是一个新的以行分隔的列表
Probably just a new line separated list.
我在这个应用程序中这样做的方式
The way that I've done it in this application
就是名字 然后是新行、分数、新行、名字、新行、分数
is just names, and then new line, score, new line, name, new line, score.
10 也就是20排
10, so 20 rows.
这就完成了工作
And that gets the job done.
假设您没有篡改文件 那么一切都应该正常工作
Assuming that you don't tamper with the file, then everything should work.
您还可以编写其他代码
And you can write additional code as well
说 哦 如果有分数 那就是全部
to say, oh, if there is a score that's all
乱码 我们没有足够的分数 那么很可能
garbled, we don't have enough scores, then probably
应该相应地呈现它
should render it accordingly.
我的代码执行类似的操作 但不完全是这样
My code does something similar to this, but not entirely.
相关代码--我将对其进行简单介绍
The relevant code-- and I'm going to sort of just glaze over it.
如果我们在看--这是突破口11 对吗？
If we're looking at-- this is Breakout11, right?
嗯
Yeah.
哦 不 这是《突破10》
Oh, no, this is Breakout10.
所以在《突破10》中 我们必须加载所有的高分
So in Breakout10, we have to load all the high scores
在Main.Lua中 它就在这里
in main.lua, which is here.
因此将身份设置为Breakout或创建一个名为Breakout文件夹
So set identity to Breakout or create a folder called Breakout
我们可以在其中保存和读取文件
that we can save and read files to and from.
如果它不存在 那么就创建它们
If it doesn't exist, then just create them.
在这种情况下 我只是输入CTO作为我的首字母
In this case, I'm just seeding CTO my initials.
然后我乘以1000
And then I times 1,000.
所以从一万降到一千
So 10,000 down to 1,000.
只是非常简单的数据
Just very simple data.
正在写入名为Breakout.lst的文件
Writing into a file called breakout.lst.
它可以是你想要的任何东西
It can be whatever you want.
我们所做的只是从数据或文件中读取行
All we're doing is reading lines from the data, or from the file.
然后这是如果它不存在的话
And then this is if it doesn't exist.
如果它确实存在 那么我们将对其进行迭代
And then if it does exist, then we're going to iterate over it
使用love.filesystem.line 它将接受一个文件
with love.filesystem.line, which will take a file
然后基本上把它分成新的行 然后给你
and then just split it on new lines basically and give you
所有这些行的迭代器
an iterator over all those lines.
所以它可以说 好的 如果它是一个名字 哪一个
So it can just say, OK, if it's a name, which
也就是说 如果名单上有一个、三个、五个或七个
means that if it's one or three or five or seven in the list,
然后将名称设置为--
then set the name to--
我们使用的是字符串.sub.以防他们
and we're using string.sub just in case they
写一些长名字 或者写一些长名字--他们做不到
write some long name or some long name gets-- they can't do it
通过我们的游戏 但如果它以某个长名称写入文件
through our game, but if it gets written to the file as some long name,
它应该被截断为三个字符
it should get truncated to three characters
这样我们就可以适当地展示它
so we can display it appropriately.
否则 如果我们不是在名字线上
And then otherwise if we're not on a name line,
如果我们在一条奇数或偶数行上
if we're on, like, an odd line or even line,
我们应该认为这是一个分数 只使用数字
we should consider that a score and just use to number.
因为我们使用字符串数据 如果我们尝试赋值
Because we're using string data and if we try to assign,
对字符串数据进行任何类型的数字比较
do any sort of comparisons numerically on the string data,
我们将不得不这样做 以比较高分
which we will have to do to compare high scores,
它不会起作用 因为它会看到有弦
it's not going to work because it's going to see that there's strings.
所以我们在这里用数字
So we use to number here.
只是一个简单的Lua函数
Just a simple Lua function.
然后就是这样
And then that's it.
然后我们只需返回分数
And then we just return scores.
然后我会找出问题的起因
And then I'll sort out what's causing the issue,
然后尽快把它推到回购上
and then push that to the repo ASAP.
但这样做的效果是 我们实际上能够加载我们所有的高分
But that has the effect of us being able to actually load all of our high scores
并在游戏开始时展示它们
and display them at the start of the game.
它不需要考虑能够实际输入我们的分数
It doesn't take care of being able to actually input our score.
因此 我们可以使用Breakout 11来实现这一点 如果运行回购 您可以看到这一点
And so we can do this with Breakout11, which you can see if you run the repo.
您可以通过测试将初始分数分配给某个值 例如10,000
And you can test just to assign your initial score to some value like 10,000
或者20,000 然后故意输掉 而你
or 20,000, and then just lose on purpose and you
了解它的实际工作原理
get a sense of how it actually works.
但从本质上说 这只是一种街机风格
But essentially, it's just arcade style.
你知道吗 你只有三个字可以输入你的名字
You know, you had only three characters you could input your name.
那么 有谁知道我们是如何存储这些东西的
So does anybody have any idea as to how we are sort of storing this,
或者可以提出一个想法？
or can pitch an idea?
所以我们有三个角色 我们想--
So we have three characters and we want to--
理想情况下 如果我们是 假设我想在第一个数上转到C
ideally if we're, let's say I want to go to C on the first one.
比方说 我按了两次 这样我就到了C 从A到C怎么样？
Let's say I pressed up twice so I get to C. How is it going from A to C?
你可以只说 你可以只渲染
You could just say, you could just render
我想要渲染角色A 角色A 角色A
I want to render the character A, the character A, the character A,
但它怎么知道你什么时候想去B、C或D呢？
but how is it going to know when you want to go to B, or C, or D.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：投球是 你可以创造
COLTON OGDEN: The pitch was, you could create
一个包含所有字符的表 并对其进行迭代
a table with all of the characters and iterate through it.
你绝对可以做到的
You absolutely could do that.
它有一点笨重
It's a little bit bulky.
这可能就是...
That might be what--
事实上 这可能不是街机系统当年的做法
actually, that's probably not how arcade systems did it back in the day.
因为在《越狱11》中我们要做的是
Because the way that we're going to do it here in Breakout11 is I
添加了一个名为EnterHighScoreState的新状态
added a new state called EnterHighScoreState.
如果你还记得的话 CS50教授了这一点
And if you recall, CS50 teaches this.
但归根结底 所有类型的字符都只是数字
But all sort of characters at the end of the day are just numbers.
ASCI
ASCI.
在这个例子中 如果你还记得的话 65是大写的A
In this case, 65, if you recall, is capital A.
所以我们要做的就是画出那个角色
So all we need to do is just draw out whatever that character
转换为字符串是或字符
cast to a string is, or character.
我们在下面的DRAW函数中简单地完成这项工作
And we do that simply down here in the draw function.
如果我们做string.char at char就是3
If we do string.char, at char is three.
所做的一切只会产生这样的效果
All that has the effect of doing is just taking that number
然后将其转换为字符
and then converting it to a character.
那么我们所需要做的就是什么？
So all we need to do then is what?
当我们想要从A到B B到C C到D
When we want to go from A to B, B to C, C to D.
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：没错
COLTON OGDEN: Exactly.
但如果我们在A 我们想往下走 会发生什么？
But then what happens if we're at A and we want to go down?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：我们会的
COLTON OGDEN: We would.
所以 如果我们在A 那么如果我们向下按 我们想要到Z
So if we're at A, then if we press downward and we want to go to Z,
其中的逻辑就在这里
the logic is in here.
但是我们增加了代码 如果它大于90 也就是Z
But one we've incremented our code, if it's greater than 90, which is Z,
那我们应该把它调回65
then we should set it back to 65.
我们将循环回A
We'll loop back to A.
这里也是一样的
And same thing here.
如果我们按下 我们在A 我们必须回到Z
If we press down and we're at A, we've got to go back up to Z,
所以我们把它设为90
so we just set it to 90.
如此简单的环回逻辑
So simple loop back logic.
我们只是把它画出来 我们突出显示
And we just draw it, we highlight.
一旦我们这样做了 用户就按Enter键
And then once we've done that, the user presses Enter.
实际上 我们过渡到High ScoreState
We transition to the HighScoreState, actually,
因为只有当他们进入新的最高分时 这种状态才会触发
because this state should only trigger if they entered a new high score.
这意味着我们需要登记到VictoryState 或者不是VictoryState
Which means that we need to check in the VictoryState, or not the VictoryState,
而是在GameOverState中 无论是否
but rather in the GameOverState whether or not
他们的分数比任何一家商店都要高
their score is higher than any of the stores in some sort of,
引用不引用 全球分数表
quote unquote, global scores table.
然后我们认为我们现在是如何来回传递分数的呢？
And then how do we think we're passing the scores back and forth now?
有人记得我们是如何跟踪应用程序状态的吗？
Does anybody recall how we're keeping track of app state?
观众：[听不见]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
在更改功能中
In the change function.
所以我们要做的就是跟踪--加载
So all we need to do is keep track of-- load
我们在比赛开始时的高分
our high scores at the beginning of the game,
把它们一直传到最后
pass them all the way down the line.
最后--我们还可以将它们加载到EnterHighScoreState中
And then finally-- and we can also load them in our EnterHighScoreState,
但我们需要跟踪我们在GameOverState中的高分是多少
but we need to keep track of what our high scores are in the GameOverState
这样我们就知道 哦 我得了高分
so that we know, oh, I've got a high score.
与其转换回StartState 不如让我们转换
Let's instead of transitioning back to the StartState, let's transition
添加到EnterHighScoreState 以便用户可以将他们的高分添加到列表中
to the EnterHighScoreState so the user can add their high score to the list.
然后一旦他们进入了他们的高分 也就是这里
And then once they've entered their high score, which is here,
我们只需将其再次写入此文件
we'll just write it to this file again.
编译一个分数字符串 它接受我们的分数的名称和分数
Compile a score string, which takes name and score of our scores.
我们拿我们当时的分数 那是--
We take whatever score that we were at that's--
我们倒着看我们的分数表
we look through our scores table backwards
当我们找到比我们的分数低的分数时
and when we find a score that's lower than ours,
我们只是跟踪这个指数 直到我们得到一个比我们的指数更高的指数
we just keep track of that index until we get to one that's higher than ours.
在这种情况下 一加一 该指数加一
In which case the one plus one, that index plus one
是我们应该改写的内容
is what we should then overwrite.
因此 我们相应地将下面的所有其他部分移位
And so we shift all the other ones below accordingly.
如果好奇的话 我们在这节课上也会这么做
And we do that in this class if curious.
所以我要轻松地看完最后一对选手
And so I'm just going to breeze through the last couple.
Ppale SELECT更新只是一种模糊状态
The paddle select update is just kind of a fluffy state
这让我们可以在我们的游戏中添加一些元素 比如用户选择
that lets us add a element of sort of, like, user selection to our game.
在我们的PaddleSelectState中 我们立即进行转换
In our PaddleSelectState here, we transition immediately.
而不是现在去[INAUDIBLE]PlayState
Instead of going to the [INAUDIBLE] PlayState now,
当我们点击开始游戏时 我们将从开始到划桨选择
we're going to go from Start to Paddle Select when we hit Start Game.
所以我们要去...
So we're going to go to--
然后是Paddle Select类本身
and then the Paddle Select class itself.
CurrentPaddle得到一个 然后它基本上
CurrentPaddle gets one, and then all it essentially
我们在这里画两个箭头
is is us drawing two arrows here.
所以如果我们是第一名--在这个例子中 我想我们是第三名--
And so if we're at number one-- in this case, I think we're at number three--
那么这两个箭头都将是完全不透明的
then both of these arrows will be completely opaque.
但如果我们在左边或右边 他们应该变暗对我们说
But if we're on the left or the right edge, they should darken to say to us,
我们不能再左右移动了因为我们
oh, we can't move left or right anymore because we're
在索引1或4或5处 只有那么多颜色
at either index one or four or five, and there's only that many colors.
然后渲染这个颜色变量
And then render whatever that color variable
就是用我们之前用过的四元表
is using the quads table that we had before of the different tables.
然后只是指令
And then just instructions.
然后从那里我们将最终过渡到ServeState
And then from there is where we'll end up transitioning to the ServeState
而不是从StartState转到ServeState
rather than going to the ServeState from the StartState.
所有的代码都在这里
And all the code in that is here.
我们在放音效
We have sound effects playing.
然后确保我们也播放不同的声音
And then making sure that we also play a different sound
效果取决于它们是在左边还是右边
effect based upon whether they're at the left or the right edge.
如果他们在左边想往左走
If they're on the left edge and they try to go left,
它应该像一个声音 听起来有点粗糙
it should play like a sound that sort of sounds a little rougher
让他们知道不能向左走
to let them know that they can't go left,
而右边缘则相反
and the opposite for the right edge.
一旦他们按下回车键
And then once that's all done, once they press Enter on whatever paddle
他们想要 他们会得到球拍
they want, they're going to get the paddle,
我们将实例化一个paddle 将其传递到ServeState
we're going to instantiate a paddle, pass that into the ServeState,
and we're going to take current当前Paddle桨from the state状态 which哪一个
and we're going to take currentPaddle from the state, which
就是他们在不同的拨片之间滚动得到的值
is whatever value they got by scrolling between all the different paddles.
然后是最后一个更新 这是几乎每堂课我最喜欢的部分
And then the last update, which is my favorite part of most every lecture
我想是音乐的更新
I think is the music update.
而所有这一切实际上只是音乐集发挥在主要.lua
And all that really is is just music set play in main.lua,
然后将循环设置为真 这样就有了一个博弈
and then set looping to true, and then we have a game.
这是我们的Paddle Select
And this is our Paddle Select.
请注意 左右两边的箭头是半透明的
So notice the arrows are semi-opaque on the left and the right.
听起来有点难 但当我现在按下
It's kind of hard to hear, but when I press right now
有点像是有一点粗糙的声音
it's kind of like there's a bit of a rougher sound.
我们选择红色
We choose red.
我们转到第一级 然后转换到ServeState
We go to level one and we transition to the ServeState
PaddleSelectState 然后我们就像往常一样玩游戏
from the PaddleSelectState, and then we just play the game as normal.
这基本上就是它的全部
And that's basically all there is to it.
有几个功能我们没有时间去真正了解
And there is a couple of features we didn't have time to really go over
比如确保我们在一定数量的点数
like making sure we recover HP if a certain amount of points
已经过去了 但我鼓励你去看看
have been elapsed, but I encourage you to look
当你触发一次命中的时候
into that when you trigger a hit.
在PlayState中有一些逻辑可以说 哦
There's some logic in the PlayState to say, oh,
如果他们已经超过了当前的复苏门槛
if they've gone over a current recovery threshold,
让我们为球员增加一颗心 你知道的 让他们继续比赛
let's add one heart to the player, you know, just keep them playing.
只是为了奖励他们的高分
Just to reward them for their high score.
下一次我们将介绍一些概念
Next time we'll cover a few concepts.
所以基本的着色器
So basic shaders.
着色器就像可以在显卡上运行的小程序
Shaders are like little programs you can run in your graphics card
并制作奇特的效果 但我们不会深入到太多细节
and do fancy effects, but we won't go into too much detail.
匿名函数
Anonymous functions.
我们在Lua中看到了很多关于Love的匿名函数
We've seen a lot of anonymous functions in Lua in the context of Love.
它们只是没有名称的函数 您可以
They're just functions without a name, and you can just
将它们用作函数参数 并用它们做各种很酷的事情
use them as function arguments and do all sorts of cool stuff with them.
下周我们做事的时候 我们会用它们做回调
We'll use them for callbacks next week when we do things
比如Twening 它正在获得一些价值
like tweening, which is taking some value
并让它随着时间的推移插入到其他东西中
and making it interpolate over time to some other thing.
因为现在我们基本上只是根据速度进行更新
Because right now we've basically just been updating things based on velocity,
但我们并没有真正按照时间来做任何事情
but we haven't really done anything based on time.
所以我们将更详细地了解这一点
So we'll take a look at that in more detail
下周将有一个名为Timer的图书馆 这真的很棒
next week with a library called timer, which is really fantastic.
允许您对事物进行计时 然后将事物链接在一起
Lets you time things and then chain things together.
如果熟悉的话 我们会报道第三场比赛
We'll be covering the game Match Three if familiar.
这基本上就是糖果粉碎传奇
It's basically Candy Crush.
我们将使用不同的瓷砖设置 但这是相同的想法
We'll be using a different tile set, but it's the same idea.
我们将不得不计算如何真正找出
And we'll have to calculate how to actually find out
无论我们是否在网格中找到了匹配 我们的瓷砖网格
whether we've gotten a match in the grid, our tile grid,
然后相应地移动这些块 然后做所有其他逻辑 加分数
and then shift the blocks accordingly and do all the other logic, add score.
然后基本上 因为它是糖果粉碎传奇和游戏的基础
And then basically since it's so fundamental to Candy Crush and games
对于它的本质 我们将不得不讨论如何在某种程度上生成
of its nature, we will have to cover how to sort of generate
这些地图在程序上具有动态布局的瓦片
these maps procedurally to have tiles that are laid out in a dynamic way,
在某种程度上 也不是从任何火柴开始
and also in a way that doesn't start off with any matches
因为那就没有任何意义了 因为比赛已经
because then that wouldn't make any sense because the matches have
来解决问题
to resolve.
如果下周有时间的话我们会抽出一点时间
And then we'll take a little time if we have the time next week
再次谈论精灵艺术和调色板
to talk about sprite art again and palettes.
也许我会向你们展示如何将图像从一个
And maybe I'll show you guys how to sort of convert images from one
调色板到另一个 比如 我使用的一个程序 Aseprite
palette to another in, like, a program that I use, Aseprite,
但你可以在任何类型的大型照片编辑软件中做到这一点
but you can do this in any sort of large photo editing software.
第二项任务是《越狱》的几个扩展
And then assignment two is a couple of extensions to Breakout.
所以如果你注意到床单上有几个小精灵
So if you noticed in the sheet there were a few little sprites here
在底部--
at the bottom--
所以 去掉四边形轮廓吧
so get rid of the quad outlines.
所以下面这些小东西 我猜
So these little things down here are, I'm assuming,
它们应该是能量充沛的
they're meant to be power ups.
它们看起来像是通电了
They look like power ups.
但pset的目标是实现通电
But the goal of the pset is to implement a power up.
一旦启动 当你抓住它的时候
And a power up is going to be such that when you grab it,
你会得到两个额外的球 或者实际上你想要多少球
you'll get two additional balls, or however many you want actually,
它将在你的那个之外产生 并自己检测碰撞
that will spawn in addition to your one and detect collisions on their own.
所以你会有几个 他们会为你得分
So you'll have several and they'll score points for you.
当然 只有当最后一个球落在屏幕表面以下时
And, of course, only when the last ball comes below the surface of the screen
你是否应该触发一场游戏结束
should you trigger a Game Over.
然后我想让你们加上--这也会
And then I want you to add-- and this will also
比说明书更详细--但我会
be more detailed than the spec-- but I would
喜欢你把成长和萎缩加到桨上
like you to add growing and shrinking to the paddle.
所以目前 我们有四种不同大小的球拍
So currently, we have like four different sizes of paddle,
但我们没有使用它们
but we're not using them.
所以如果我们得到了足够的分数或我们失去了分数 那就好了
So it would be nice if when we gain enough points or we lose points, or not
分数 而不是生活 我们增加或减少桨的大小
points, but lives rather, we increase or decrease the size of the paddle
因此 我们要引入另一个层面的挑战
accordingly just to introduce another level of challenge
或者缺乏挑战
and or lack of challenge.
最后 最后一部分也在精灵表中
And then finally, one last part which is in the sprite sheet as well,
这里有一个钥匙块 这里有一个钥匙电源
there's a key block here and a key power up here.
所以让力量来 用你的桨把力量捡起来
So sort of let the power up come, pick the power up with your paddle.
只有当你有了这种力量
And then only when you have that power up should you
能用钥匙打破障碍
be able to break the block with a key.
你应该考虑到这点
And you should take this into consideration
你也可以在生成水平时使用
when generating your levels as well.
所以你也必须用水平仪弄脏你的手
So you'll have to also get your hands dirty with the level maker.
但总的来说 这就是突破
But all in all, that was Breakout.
我们下次见
So I'll see you guys next time.
谢谢
Thank you.